<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An instruction how to pray and meditate well Distinguished into thirtie six chapters. Composed at the request of certaine louers of pietie, desirous to aduance themselues in perfection. By the Reuerend Father, Ignatius Balsamo Priest of the Societie of Iesus. And translated out of French into English, by Iohn Heigham.</title>
            <author>Balsamo, Ignazio, 1543-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 171 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847380</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847380</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03296)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1194:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An instruction how to pray and meditate well Distinguished into thirtie six chapters. Composed at the request of certaine louers of pietie, desirous to aduance themselues in perfection. By the Reuerend Father, Ignatius Balsamo Priest of the Societie of Iesus. And translated out of French into English, by Iohn Heigham.</title>
                  <author>Balsamo, Ignazio, 1543-1618.</author>
                  <author>Heigham, John, fl. 1639.</author>
                  <author>Everard, Thomas, 1560-1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>331, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Which licence of superiors [C. Boscard for J. Heigham],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At S. Omers :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>The translation is in conjunction with Thomas Everard.</note>
                  <note>"The flowers of deuotion" has subsidiary title page on T7r; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AN</hi> INSTRVCTION How to Pray and <hi>Meditate well.</hi> DISTINGVISHED Into Thirtie ſix Chapters. <hi>COMPOSED At the requeſt of certaine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of Pietie, deſirous to aduance themſelues in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the Reuerend Father, IGNATIVS BALSAMO <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the Societie of IESVS.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And tranſlated out of French into English, by</hi> IOHN HEIGHAM.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At S. Omers.</hi> Which licence of Superiors Anno 1622.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12413:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WORTHIE AND VERTVOVS Ladie, the Ladie LOVELL</head>
                  <p>RIght worthie <hi>MADAME</hi> Hauing in my handes an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortiue infant, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12413:3"/> hath a father, but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth a mother, my breast (the tables wherein I euer write the loues of thoſe to whom I am obliged) had many impulſions, hamblie to preſent this litle gift to your protection; encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this, that honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons, doe not bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance oblations according to their bignes; nor weigh ſo much the gifte, as the good will of the giuer; nor yet reſpect the matter, but the mind of the offerer</p>
                  <p>You are not ignorant, that euen the verie left
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12413:3"/> things in this world, ar of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times thoſe which, of the moſt noble &amp; curious of all, are chieflie required. Orient pearles are litle in quantitie, but riche in apri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ment. Archimides ſphere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained no more in its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure, ſaue onlie the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a hazell nut, but for that it ſo ingeniouſlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented what ſo euer was admirable in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heauens, it rauished the ſpirits of all behoulders</p>
                  <p>Holie Scripture doth alſo teache vs, that the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12413:4"/> daughter of kinge Pharao was not offended at the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes of Moyſes (whom she termed ſo, becauſe she tooke him foorth of the vvaters) moued vvith pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and commiſeration to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, by reaſon of the ſingular beautie vvhich shined in him.</p>
                  <p>This motherles childe, of far greater price then any Orient pearle, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſurpaſsing Alchimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Sphere, &amp; shining in al ſort of beautie like the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Moyſes, might happelie neuertheles haue incurred
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12413:4"/> like misfortune, if he had not had the good hap, to be taken vp into the armes of ſo worthy a mother as your ſelfe, far ſurpaſsing Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Pharaos daughter, in pittie, compaſsion, vvith many other diuine and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie virtues, vvhereof that vnchristian Queene muſt needes be incapable.</p>
                  <p>Conceiue then (Right Curteous Madam I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you) of this my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as of a pearle of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable price, or at the leaſt, as of a Meſſenger by vvhom I ſende you, my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12413:5"/> best, my truest, and hartiest <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire of your ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit &amp; aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in virtu. If I haue offended in preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to write without ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient pretext, to ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a perſon your ſelf (vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Madam) be pleaſed at the leaſt to disburthen me of ſome part of the bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, finding my ſelfe bound here vnto, by the ſundrie bondes of honor, benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with diuers most ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fauours which you haue demonſtrated both vnto me, and to myne: which, together with your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12413:5"/> gular pietie and zeale to virtu, haue preſſed my pen, in part to acquit me of mine owne dutie, and of your deſert Wishing you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall encreaſe of all vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, with long life, health, and happines in this world and euerlaſting life in the next, I take my leaue, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning euermore.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladiſhips hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy goſſip. IOHN HEIGHAM.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12413:6"/>
                  <head>AN INSTRVCTION How to Pray and <hi>Meditate well.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the exerciſes of a ſpirituall life, there is none more difficult, nor more neceſſarie, then the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Prayer, &amp; medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:12413:6"/> the which many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſon ages haue wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, &amp; reaſon and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience do ſufficientlie ſhew vs: wherfor on the behalfe of man is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a great deſire, care &amp; diligence in this affaire. One may learne to pray well in three maners, or by three particular mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. The firſt meanes, or Maiſter, is, the holie Ghoſt: for if all thinges be the gift of almightie God, ſpecialy the gift of Praier, is this gift. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12413:7"/> aske the ſame of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, ſaying with the Apoſtles (Luc. 11) <hi>Domine doce nos orare.</hi> Lord reach vs to pray, for if thou (ô Lord) teach vs not to pray, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhal we knowe how to pray well.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond meanes is, the ſelfe ſame Prayer, my meaning is, that in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; meditating, a man ſhal learne how to pray &amp; meditate, as other arts or occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And euen as hee who ſhould not write at al, or onely once
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12413:7"/> in a moneth, ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer learne to write: ſo he who neuer, or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ldom prayeth and Meditateth shal neuer learne to pray &amp; Meditate. The third Maiſter ſhall be, ſome ſpiritual Father, wel ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in theſe affaires. For as S. Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith, writing to Ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, de Monach<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inſtitut. <hi>Nulla ars ſine Magistro.</hi> None can euer learne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny art without a Maiſter: whence we read in the Goſpel of S. Luke (c. 11) that S. Iohn Bap. taught
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12413:8"/> his diſciples to pray, and our Lord &amp; Sauiour his.</p>
                     <p>To Meditate &amp; make Mentall Prayer, two things are verie neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to witte, the Manner, and the Matter, that is to ſay, that one muſt knowe the methode how to doe it, and next haue the ſubiect in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, to employ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therevpon: and for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of theſe two things or of the one of them, many are caſt backward, and cannot attende to this holie Exerciſe. We
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12413:8"/> will endeuour then, to aide them in the other. But firſt we muſt note and vnderſtande two things; The one, what Prayer, Meditation, and their ſpecies meaneth; The other, what things helpe, and what things hinder Prayer, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>An Explication of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Prayer, Meditation, and ſuch others.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis worde Prayer, is taken in three
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12413:9"/> manners, the ſecond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt proper. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Prayer is called Petition, in Engliſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, or requeſt: ſo S. Iohn Damaſcen taketh it. (Lib. 3. <hi>de Fide</hi> cap. 24.) when he ſaith. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio est Petitio decentium à Deo.</hi> Prayer is a dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Almightie God, of thinges that are decent.</p>
                     <p>Othertimes, <hi>Prayer</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the ſpeech, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or Colloquie of the ſoule with Almighty God, be it in in asking ſomthing of him, be it in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12413:9"/> thanking him, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conferring with him. And in this ſence S. Chriſoſtome taketh it (Hom 10. in Gen.) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ortio eſt colloquium cum Deo.</hi> Prayer is a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie of the ſoule with Almightie God.</p>
                     <p>Other times, this worde <hi>Prayer</hi> ſignifieth genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly al the interiour acts of the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, of the will, and of the other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, when they ar ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed to almighty God. And in the ſame ſence, the ſelfe-ſame S. Iohn
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12413:10"/> Damaſcene ſaith in the place before alleadged, <hi>Oratio eſt aſcenſus mentis in Deum.</hi> Prayer is the aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vp of the mind into Almighty God; So that Meditation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, Prayſing of God, Thankſgiuing, Petition, Obſecration, Oblation, Promiſe, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of a mans ſelfe, Complaint, Examen of Conſcience, Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and other like Actes, are all ſpecies of Prayer; and to Meditate, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template, Giue Than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Offer, and examine
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12413:10"/> of Conſcience, all this is Prayer; yea, to reade ſome ſpiritual booke by way of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is alſo to Pray. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in this faſhion, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God ſpeaketh with man, as in praying man ſpeaketh with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. For this cauſe S. Bernard in his book. <hi>De ſcala Clauſtraliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> hath placed the reading of ſpirituall bookes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the parts of Praier</p>
                     <p>To Meditate, is as much to ſay, as to thinke on ſome kinde of thing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12413:11"/> or matter diligentlie, &amp; attentiuelie, to the end to pray, and to ſpeake, with God. This I ſaye, becauſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider ſome myſterie of our faith, or other like thing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate in claſſe, or for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like ende, is not an eſpece of Prayer.</p>
                     <p>This Meditation, or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, is an acte of the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce foorthwith folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the acte of the will; for man knowing ſome good or euill, moueth it to loue or hate the ſame,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12413:11"/> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the Holy Prophet ſaid. Pſal. 38. <hi>In medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion emea exardeſcet ignis.</hi> In my Meditation, fire ſhall be kindled within myne heart. And for this reaſon it is, that Prayer &amp; Meditation, goe ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie together, and are in ſuch wiſe conioyned, that oftentimes one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not treate of the one, without the other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Contemplation,</hi> is an excellent and affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meditation, which is made without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and without
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12413:12"/> paine, the ſoule being vnited with his God both byknowledge &amp; loue together, as one who beholdeth ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a beautifull Image, without moouing his fight this way, or that way, and therein taking his contentment.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Prayſe of God,</hi> is to laud and bleſſe him, for the vertues and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ained in him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thankeſgiuiing,</hi> is to render him Thankes for the benefites we haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12413:12"/> receaued of him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Petition,</hi> or demaund is ſimply to aske ſome thing of him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obſecration,</hi> is a dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d interpoſing ſome other ſacred thing agreable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to the end to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne him: as ſaying, by the pretious blod of thy Sonne, I beſeech thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Oblation,</hi> is to offer ſome thing vnto him, as our ſoule, our bodie, or the workes which wee performe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Examen of Conſcience,</hi> is to ſearch out our faults
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12413:13"/> before Almighty God to craue pardon, &amp; to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d and correct our ſelues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Admiration,</hi> is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent act of Prayer, when the ſoule being in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, commeth to wonder, &amp; to be aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at the Wiſdome, Bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty Patience, &amp; other works of almighty God: whence do follow Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ſometimes Extaſies, or Rauiſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</p>
                     <p>Now taking Prayer properlie in the ſecond ſignification, there are three ſortes of Prayers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12413:13"/> to witte, Mentall, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and Mixt. And the reaſon is, for that in three ſorts or manners, a man may ſpeake with Almighty God, by Hart, by Mouth, and with the one and the other together: but we are to vnderſtand them well.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mentall Prayer</hi> is, when the ſoule ſpeaketh to God interiourlie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pronouncing any worde at all, ſhewing vnto him what ſhe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, with the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lippes; This is true
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12413:14"/> and perfect Prayer, &amp; in the which God delights him, as our Sauiour ſaid to the Samaritan wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (S. Iohn cap. 4) <hi>God is a ſpirit, &amp; they that adore him, must adore in in ſpirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vocall prayer,</hi> is that which is made with the voice, forming and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing the wordes; But marke, that this ought to proceede fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hart, that is to ſay, that wee muſt conſider the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which we ſpeake, or haue at the leaſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12413:14"/> to Praye, for if one Pray onely with the Mouthe, without any inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, vſing no inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour todriue away diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions, and the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of the ſpirit; ſuch Prayer is neither vocall Prayer, nor any Prayer, but rather ſinne, the which God reproacheth vnto his people by the Prophet Eſay (cap. 29. &amp; in Mat. cap. 5.) ſaying. <hi>This people honoureth mee with their lippes, but their heart is farre from mee:</hi> This Prayer therefore,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12413:15"/> is not called Vocall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is made onelie with the mouth, but to be diſtinguiſhed from that which is Mentall: becauſe that Mentall Prayer is made with the heart onelie, and Vocall, by adding to the thoughts, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des alſo.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mixt Prayer,</hi> is as much to ſaye, as compoſed of Mental and Vocal toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and is, when a man Prayeth vnto God, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by heart, partlie by by mouth; ſo that it is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12413:15"/> not mixt Prayer, when on prayeth with ſpirit &amp; word together, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or pondering what one ſaith (as ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) but it, is Vocall Prayer. But mixt Praier, is ſo called, when after one hath prayed in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he doe adde thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome prayer by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12413:16"/>
                     <head>CHAP. III <hi>Of that which we must do, and whereof we must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, to the end, to Pray and Meditate well.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere are verie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie things which further, &amp; are requiſite, yea, verie neceſſarie, to Pray and Meditate wel; &amp; likewiſe many which doe hinder, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we muſt carefuly take heede. And this is one of the cauſes, for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12413:16"/> which this exerciſe is ſo difficult: it is alſo the cauſe, that there are ſo fewe in the worlde that doe performe it wel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we bring not that which the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, nor countergarde our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are contrarie; which thinge, euerie one may know, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelfe, after wee ſhal ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e explicated the the ſame. Of theſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and impediments, the R. F. Lewis of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nade, hath treated won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12413:17"/> well, and amplie in his ſecond booke of Prayer and Meditation.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The time.</head>
                        <p>Firſt, hee muſt deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and ſet downe, a certaine time, to employ in this holie exerciſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie day. And touching the ſame, ſundry things are to be noted.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Firſt that one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not giue a general rule for all, to employ thus much or thus much time becauſe of the great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of perſons, Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, euery on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12413:17"/> according to his eſtate, ought to depute one hower, or at the leaſt halfe an hower, or two howres, or as ſhal ſeeme beſt vnto himſelfe: and withall, to determine the howre wherin he doe the ſame, either in in the morning, or in ſome other time.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Hauing reſolued to allow ſo much time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Prayer and Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and at ſuch an houre, he muſt neither omit it for any affayre in the worlde (vnderſtanding
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12413:18"/> that this buſines is of the greateſt importance of all others, and ought to be preferred before al others) nor change the ſame into an other hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re; for the ſubtile enemy endeuoureth to haue it deferred to another time more inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious, to render the Praier &amp; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarion ſo much the worſe, or wholy to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it: nor to cut off, or ſhorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time deſigned whereof ſhall be ſpoken after. Neuertheleſſe, this ought to be vnderſtood,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12413:18"/> ſauing obedience &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: for if whileſt we pray, either our Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cal vs, or ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of Charitie preſents it ſelfe to aſſiſt our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, wee ought then to leaue Prayer, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Almighty God wil haue it ſo, &amp; we ſhal haue the greater merit.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. When ſuch a caſe ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we leaue for iuſt cauſe, one parte, or al our Praier, we muſt not forget to recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the ſame, and to doe it ſome other time,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12413:19"/> on the ſame daye, if it may be poſſible: euen as he who hauing bin let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dine at his accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed houre, doth not forget to take his refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction afterwardes.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. The time moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to attend to Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Mental Praier, is the Mid-night, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of the great ſilence &amp; quietneſſe thereof. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this time, the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning houldeth the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rancke, after we are vp, &amp; before wee ſet hand to any other worke or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12413:19"/> ſtudie. For in the firſt place (as our Sauiour ſaith in S. Matthew, cap. 6.) Wee muſt firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore al things, ſeeke the kingdom of God. And after the Morning, the moſt proper time is the Euening before ſupper.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. Furthermore, a fit time to pray and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate is, when the Spouſe calleth the ſoule interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourlie, &amp; preuenteth her with his heauenlie gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, in ſuch ſort that ſhee findeth her ſelfe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed to pray and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12413:20"/> Contemplate. As alſo when the ſoule longeth and deſireth to make her prayers: as the bodie, which hath an appetite to eate.</p>
                        <p>Moreouer, on Holie daies, we muſt attende a longer time to Prayer and Contemplation, and to doe no other thinge on thoſe dayes, if it be poſſible, becauſe for this they were ordained and inſtituted. And by how much the ſolemnitie, &amp; the miſterie which is ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated is greater, by ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12413:20"/> ſo much more the more ought wee to giue our ſelues to this holie exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Place.</head>
                        <p>There muſt likewiſe be a proper place, &amp; the beſt, is the moſt ſecrete and remote from noiſe, as God him-ſelfe hath taught vs, both in the new Teſtament, and in the Olde. <hi>I will lead him</hi> (ſaith the Prophet Oſe, cap. 2.) <hi>into the deſert, &amp; there will</hi> I <hi>ſpeake to his hart.</hi> And our Sauiour in the Goſpell of Saynt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12413:21"/> Matth. cap. 6. When thou ſhalt pray, enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Chamber, and hauing ſhut the doore, pray to thy Father in ſecret. And albeit this may be vnderſtood ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualy, as much to ſaye: enter within thy ſelfe, and ſhut the gate againſt all other affaires and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, yet there is no doubt, but it is to be vnderſtood alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the letter. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt ſhut the gate that none diſturbe vs, and with all the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12413:21"/> becauſe the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce which is obſcure, is the more proper and moſt doth aide the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of the ſpirit.</p>
                        <p>Alſo the Church or Chappel (prouided ther be no noyſe) is a place verie proper to Pray &amp; Conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plate, eſpecialy if the B. Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar be there. But if euery one ought to haue in his owne houſe, a deuout Oratorie, there to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelfe and to make his deuotions.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12413:22"/>
                        <head>Contrition and bodelie Chastiſement.</head>
                        <p>Pennance doth mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelloufly helpe to praye well, as well the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, which is to haue Contrition, Compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſorrowe for ſinnes, as the exterior, which is to mortifie the fleſh by Faſtinges, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines, Haire-cloth, and other auſterities, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſubiect vnto the ſpirit, &amp; by how much the more any one ſhall loue theſe two ſortes of pennance, ſo much the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12413:22"/> better will he make his Prayers &amp; meditations. And contrariwiſe, who is no great friend ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it impoſſible that he praye wel, or that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance him ſelfe in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual exerciſes; For Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Mortification, be inſeparable companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Euerie one therefore, ought to informe his Ghoſtlie father, what hee doth in this caſe, &amp; to do nothing without his aduiſe and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Abstinence.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Amongſt exteriour
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12413:23"/> Pennances, Abſtinence &amp; Faſting do helpe thee moſt to pray and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate well, becauſe Abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence doeth eaſilie ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate the ſpirite vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, as Holie Church ſingeth in time of Lent: &amp; contrarywi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, the bodie being filled with meate, doth ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpirit vnapt to his functions. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who ſo deſireth to vnite him-ſelfe with God by Prayer &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, it behoueth that he be very ſober in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12413:23"/> his eating &amp; dringing, &amp; that he haue great regard to the quantitie, quality, &amp; maner of eating, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing &amp; mortifying his ſenſualitie, as much as hee may; being wholy perſwaded (as trueit is) that the ſenſual man can neuer Pray nor Meditate wel, becauſe the fleſh &amp; the ſpirit are things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And this ſobriety, is eſpeciallie requiſite in the Euening, to the end to be the better diſpoſed to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to deuotion in the Morning.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:12413:24"/>
                        <head>Silence and keeping of the ſenſes.</head>
                        <p>No leſſe requiſite and neceſſarie is, the careful keeping of the Tongue, and of the other Senſes, as the Seeing, and the Hearing; Becauſe curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie to ſee and to heare, cauſeth diſtraction, and hindereth deuotion (and to talke much, a great deale more.) as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, taciturnitie, and not to care to ſee and to heare, dooth greatlie helpe to conſerue the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12413:24"/> ſame wherefore, who ſo deſireth to profite in this holie exerciſe ought to be verie vigilant, to keepe theſe gates or paſſages carefully ſhut, to wit, the mouth, the eyes, and the eares, and to liue, as much as he may, as one du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be, blinde, and deafe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Solitude, Recollection, and Iaculatorie Prayer.</head>
                        <p>For the ſelfe-ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Solitude &amp; Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of a mans ſelfe, are ſingular helpes to Pray and Meditate Wel,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12413:25"/> that is to ſay, to be reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and to loue his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and not to conuerſe with men no more then neceſſitie doeth require. Alſo alwayes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne him within himſelfe, &amp; recollected in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admidſt exterior oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vſing ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory Praiers, which is a thing exceeding profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; For in ſo doing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time of Prayer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth, a man is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſpoſed, foorth with entreth &amp; findeth what
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12413:25"/> he deſireth. But contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the man that is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, when the time of Prayer arriueth, he findeth in himſelfe great paine, hauing his ſpirit filled with diuers fancies of which hee cannot ridde himſelfe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Multitude of affaires.</head>
                        <p>For the ſame cauſe alſo, one of the thinges which do moſt hinder Prayer &amp; Meditation, is to haue ouermanie affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and occupations, what ſoeuer they be, in which the time paſſeth,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12413:26"/> and diſtraction entreth, and our vnderſtanding becometh drye and taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe towardes ſpirituall thinges. Wherein oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the enemie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyleth, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie deceaueth ſundry zealous ſeruants of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, making them to addict themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues ouermuch to ſuch affayres, and to forget themſelues, or at the leaſt to poſt-poſe their owne ſaluation, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement in ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretext of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12413:26"/> honour of God, good of ſoules, charity, obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and the like, and ſee not the poore whom they oppreſſe, doing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie here in to the will of God, and peruerting both the order of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and of nature, by the which we are bound to loue our ſelues much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſarie, that euery on beware of this deuiliſh deceit, &amp; that he do not ouer-burden himſelfe, to the ende he may atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to Prayer &amp; Meditation.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12413:27"/>
                        <head>Interior peace.</head>
                        <p>As the Bridell and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ſenſes, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſarie to Praye and Meditate well (as hath bene ſaid) ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ar the mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his inward paſſions, contergarding himſelfe from all vnquietneſſe, trouble, and vexation, and from all diſordinate affection towardes any creature what ſoeuer, keeping him-ſelfe all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in true peace and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quility of ſpirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12413:27"/> looſing the ſame for any euent or worldly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; For it written (Pſal 75.) <hi>Factus eſt in pacelocus eius.</hi> God doth lodge in the place of peace; and into troubled waters, one cannot ſee clearely.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Spirituall Lecture and Health of the body.</head>
                        <p>Spirituall Lecture, doeth greatlie helpe, Prayer and Meditation, wherefore it be hooueth to haue ſpiritual bookes, and ſometimes to ſerue a mans ſelfe of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12413:28"/> to the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and neceſſitie of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one. Of this lecture and bookes, ſhall be ſpoken in his place.</p>
                        <p>Heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h, and the good eſtate of the bodie, is as much neceſſarie vnto this exerciſe, as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, becauſe if the bodie which is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the ſoule in its functions, be not well, the ſoule cannot pray and Meditate well; Euen as if the Penne be il made, the writers ſhal write nothing to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12413:28"/> purpoſe eſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>llie heed muſt be taken, that the he ade be well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Diſcretion with a right intention.</head>
                        <p>Albeit that to this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Prayer, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, a man muſt bring all poſſible dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, enforcing himſelfe to performe from point to point, all that which is required, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, he muſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie take heede of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12413:29"/> indiſcreete violence, in the ſoule, or to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which is, diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call illuſion, to hinder vs afterwardes to pray: as to obtaine teares by force, to conſtraine the bodie, to ſet one his knees, and to ouercome himſelfe; but hee muſt rather carrie himſelfe, ſweetly and humblie, &amp; and ſaye with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet (Pſal. 48.) <hi>Audiam quid loquatur in me Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Deus.</hi> I will liſten what my Lord God ſaith within mee.</p>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12413:29"/>
                        <p>Beſide this, hee muſt haue herein, as in euery other thing, a good &amp; holie intention, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him ſelfe, or his proper guſt and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but purely the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and good pleaſure of Almightie God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Simplicitie, Humilitie, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and Puritie of Conſcience.</head>
                        <p>Simplicitie ought to be the companion of prayer, not ſearching cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thinges in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, as are rare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, or eleuated vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12413:30"/> for God pleaſeth him not with the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but with the ſimple. <hi>Et cum ſimplic<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bus ſermoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio eius</hi> (Pro. 3.) &amp; the ſimple are more capable of Prayer &amp; Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                        <p>Alſo Humilitie, and both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reuerence, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating himſelfe before God, in hart, and in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (yet with the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid diſcretion) remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring himſelfe, that he is in the preſence of the deuine Maieſtie, as her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after shall be ſayde.</p>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:12413:30"/>
                        <p>Prayer likewiſe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a great puritie of Conſcience, and a life that is holie, for <hi>Beati mundo corde,</hi> Bleſſed are the cleane in heart (Mat. 5.) Thoſe which haue their hart pure &amp; cleane are capable to ſee All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God. This is the cauſe, that thoſe who haue a large Conſcience and make no great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of faults, which are but litle in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, ſhall neuer attaine to be men of Prayer.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:12413:31"/>
                        <head>Conference with others preparation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance.</head>
                        <p>It ſerueth alſo to pray well, to conferwith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to talke and diſcourſe of ſpirituall thinges, and concerning deuotion. For ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes doe enkindle the heart, as witneſſed the two Diſciples which went to Emaus, and our Sauiour with them, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſing of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our Redemption. (Luc. 24. 13.) Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe parſons who
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12413:31"/> pleaſe them ſelues to ſpeake of other things, ſhal neuer haue the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to Praye and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate well.</p>
                        <p>Finallie, two thinges are more neceſſarie then all others: diligent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration before Prayer, (whereof ſhall be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in his place) &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, continuing vntill the laſt hower of our life, this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and hard an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and that with a great confidence in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12413:32"/> of himſelfe, and ſurmounting all maner of difficulties which may preſent themſelues Whereunto may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, that which our Sauiour ſayeth, we muſt Praye alwayes, and not be wearie. (Luc. 18.)</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>How Mentall Prayer is to be made.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MEntall Prayer, is a Colloquie or interiour ſpeech of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12413:32"/> ſoule with Almighty God ſpeaking to him in ſpirite, what ſhe will, without exteriour wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
                     <p>This may be done in two manners. The one is, when the ſoule for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth of her ſelfe, that which ſhe ſpeaketh to Almightie God, as ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto him interiorly. My God, thou haſt done vnto me ſuch infinit good, &amp;c. I wretch that I am, I am not worthie, &amp;c. Giue me me grace &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12413:33"/>
                     <p>The other faſhion is, to paſſe in ſpirit, ſome vocall Prayer, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> &amp;c. or any other that one hath by heart, from one ende to another, preſenting vnto God the demandes and thinges contained in the wordes of the ſame Prayer.</p>
                     <p>In prayer, that is to ſaye, in ſpeaking to God, one doth, and ought to doe, three thinges ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narilie; Thanke, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, and Offer. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund conſiſteth in two
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12413:33"/> things in general, either to demaund pardon, or ſome other grace, good, vertue, or other thinge which we deſire. To doe all which, wee wil a litle ſhew the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>How we muſt render Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes vnto God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>TO render Thankes to Almightie God a man muſt haue, and know without booke, two Rolles of Benefits.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12413:34"/> The one of generail Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, which may be theſe Seauen. Creation, Conſeruation, Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, Faith (or the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian) Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (to haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted my repentance, and pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>doned my ſinnes) The Communion of his moſt ſacred bodie. And Vocation to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
                     <p>The other, of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, which euerie one himſelfe may make, as to be borne of honeſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother.</p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:12413:34"/>
                     <p>To haue a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and health. To haue bene deliuered from ſome ſickneſſe, da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or other like; and conſidering a litle euery Benefite, there is matter enough to render Than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and to ſtay himſelfe in Prayer.</p>
                     <p>And more in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, a man may render thankes in this faſhion, for the goods of Nature, of Grace, and for thoſe acquired; Of the ſoule, of the Bodie, and for Exteriour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:12413:35"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Petition, or Demaund.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IN a demaunde there are foure points, to wit; what things wee ought to demaund; For whom; Of whom; And how. And we muſt doe all things wel, to the end we may obtaine that which we demaund.</p>
                     <p>That which we ought to demand, is contayned in our Lords Prayer. But beſides theſe generall
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12413:35"/> demaunds of the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> which wee ought dailie to make in the firſt place: euery one ought alſo euerie daye to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of Almightie God, ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thinges, which are needfull vnto him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a rolle or liſt of them, and knowing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by heart, to ſerue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thereof in Mentall prayer: as for example. <hi>A Rolle or Liste of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Demaunds.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. To demaund gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, well and duelie to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12413:36"/> performe his office.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To employ the time well.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To obtaine the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his eſtate and profeſſion.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To vnquiſh ſome vice, and to extirpate ſome imperfection.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To Dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſome ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu wherof on hath moſt neceſſity eſpecialy Chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty &amp; humility, or the gift of Prayer, or of greater Faith, ſaying with the Apoſtles (Luc. 11.) <hi>Lord teach vs to pray.</hi> And Luc. 17. <hi>Lord increaſe faith in vs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12413:36"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Whereof vve muſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund pardon</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe may demaund in generall, pardon of all his offences; or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them into three partes, asking pardon of all the euill that one hath done: and of all the good, which he hath left vndone. And of all the time one hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed ill. Another generall faſhion is;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12413:37"/> to aske forgiueneſſe of our euill Thoughtes, Wordes, and workes. And of the Omiſſion of good Thoughtes, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and workes.</p>
                     <p>In particular, to fixe his mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>de vpon theſe foure points.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of Almightie God and his Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The ſeauen Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The three facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule; Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Memorie, and Will.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:12413:37"/>4. The fiue Sences of the Bodie, Seeing, Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Smelling, Taſting, and Touching.</p>
                     <p>For in theſe foure ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biects are conprehended all the ſinnes which a man may commit in his whole life: and diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon each of theſe points, on after another, to demannde pardon in particular, for ſinnes committed, againſt ſuch or ſuch a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and in ſuch a ſort of ſinne, and with ſuch a Facultie or Sence.</p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:12413:38"/>
                     <p>And beſide this, euery one may adde the ſinnes proper to his eſtate and office.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Rolle or list, of thoſefor whom vve ought to Pray.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In generall we ought to pray for all, as our Lorde hath very well ſhewed vs in the Prayer which hee hath taught vs: and for ſome more in particular. This ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may ſerue euetie one.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. For all the Holy Church, and namelie for our Holie Father the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12413:38"/> Pope, Prelates, and all Eccleſiaſticall perſons.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For the reducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heretickes, and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uerſion of Infidels.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. For all the whole Kingdome, and namelie for the King, and our Princes.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. For all Lordes and Chriſtian Princes.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For our Superiours, Gouernours, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. For our Benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors liuing &amp; departed.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. For the ſoules in in purgatorie.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:12413:39"/>8. For all thoſe which are in our charge.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. For our enemies, and aduerſaries.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Then in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, for ſuch and ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or departed, and for them alſo who haue recommended them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vnto our Prayers.</p>
                     <p>This Prayer which is made for others, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry agreable vnto almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, as S. Chriſoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome ſaith: and we both ought, and are bound thereunto, and therefore muſt euerie day, duelie
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12413:39"/> diſcharge our ſelues of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>It may likewiſe be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that as we pray and demaund for others; ſo may we render thankes and offer for others: For example.</p>
                     <p>To render thankes vnto Almightie God, for all the benefits which hee hath done to all the Angels, and to all men, and eſpecialie, to his B. Mother.</p>
                     <p>Alſo, to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
                     <p>To all Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12413:40"/> vnto this realme: to this Perſon, and to that, conſidering the the perſons, and the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites ſome what in particular, and rendring thankes to Almightie God for euerie benefite, in the ſelfe-ſame faſhion that we render thankes for our owne ſelues.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>A Rolle or List of Patrons, which wee ought to Pray vnto.</head>
                        <p>Euerie one ought to haue a Rolle or Liſt of Patrons, and to pray de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutlie vnto them euery
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12413:40"/> daye: This for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may ſeeme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Our Ladie.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. After our Ladie, our Angell Gardien.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The Saint of whom euerie one beareth the name.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Afterwardes, the Saintes to whom one hath moſt deuotion.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. The Saint or Patron of the place or countrie whereof one is: As alſo the Angell who hath the charge of the ſaid place or country.</p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <pb n="80" facs="tcp:12413:41"/>6. The Saint of the preſent day.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. The Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, may put in the fifth or fourth place, the Saint or Founder of their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The maner Howe we ought to demaunde.</head>
                        <p>To obtaine that which we demaund, three thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges there are which greatlie helpe.</p>
                        <p>The firſt is, that in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding any thinge of Almightie God, we muſt actually exerciſe <hi>Faith,</hi> conſidering that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:12413:41"/> hee can doe all things. <hi>Hope,</hi> conſidering his great bountie, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a deſire and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to obtaine our demaund. And <hi>Charitie,</hi> demanding ſuch a thing, for the deſire we haue of the honour of God, of ouraowne ſaluation, and of our neighbours.</p>
                        <p>2. The ſecond is, in demaunding, to vſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrations, as we ſee in the Litanies, and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the Church.</p>
                        <p>3. The third is, to ad immediatlie thereunto,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12413:42"/> the Interceſſion of the Saints, who can much better then we, obtaine that for vs, which we doe not merit.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>That which vve ought to offer and hovv.</head>
                        <p>We muſt offer vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Almightie God, all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> which he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, and doth daylie giue vs, our Being, our Life, our Soule, our Bodie, our exteriour goods, our thoughts our wordes; and our works.</p>
                        <p>Item, to offer vnto his Sonne, his pretious
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12413:42"/> Blood, his death &amp; paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his Merits, and his wounderfull workes.</p>
                        <p>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the good workes of his ſacred Mother, of al his Saints, &amp; of al de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout &amp; Godly people, and of all the Church, ſince the verie beginn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the worlde.</p>
                        <p>And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to offer al this, as wel for our ſelues, as for all others in general and in particular, in the ſelfe-ſame faſhion, as wee haue ſaid before, ſpeaking of Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, &amp; of Demaund.</p>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:12413:43"/>
                        <p>We muſt then doe al theſe things Mentallie; Thanke, Demaund, &amp; Offer for our ſelues, and alſo for others, for of this ſorte of Prayer, we ſpeake at this preſent; And it is an excellent meanes to remaine and continue long time in Prayer.</p>
                        <p>It is further to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that theſe things are to be done in certaine times euery day: as in the Morninng after Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or in hearing Maſſe, or after Maſſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12413:43"/> and to keepe herein good order, to the ende we fayle not: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we doe eaſilie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them, but being a litle accuſtomed therto, there is no difficultie.</p>
                        <p>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> which reſteth of Mentall Prayer, ſhall be touched hereafter, where wee will treate of Colloquies.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Mixt Prayer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MIxt Prayer, is pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perlie ſo called (as
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:12413:44"/> we before haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated) when one prayeth a litle Mentally and a litle Vocallie; as if after I haue prayed in ſpirit, for the ſoules in Purgatorie, I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite by mouth the praier <hi>Fidelium Deus omnium Conditor.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his ſort of Prayer, is much more eaſie, then Meditation and Mentall Prayer, and in particular, a man may ſerue himſelfe thereof, at ſuch time as one finds not himſelfe diſpoſed in Soule, or Bodie, to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12413:44"/> &amp; to Praye Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Firſt, one may pray in this faſhion, vpon the Commandements of Almightie God, and of the Church: as for example: To take the firſt Commandement of the Decalogue, and to conſider how euilly we haue obſerued the ſame for the time paſt, reducing a litle, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, the ſinnes that one hath committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and to aske
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12413:45"/> forgiueneſſe in heart Mentallie; and after, to recite our Lords Prayer and to doe the ſame, on each Commandement.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To make the ſame diſcourſe vpon the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen capitall ſinnes. And firſt, to reduce to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the ſinnes of Pride and the ſundry wayes that one hath offended in this ſorte of ſinne, &amp; to aske forgiueneſſe for the ſame in ſpirit: and then to adde the <hi>Pater noster</hi> vocallie.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Vpon the three Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12413:45"/> of the ſoule, the Memorie, the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and the will, vſing the ſame faſhion to Pray Mentallie, and Vocallie, after we haue a litle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as for example. Wherefore almightie God, hath giuen me Memorie, and the ſinnes which I haue committed in this facultie, not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying it as God hath willed mee, but doing the contrarie: And in the ſame ſorte, of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and the will.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The like is to bee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12413:46"/> done vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fiue Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the bodie, the Sight, the Hearing, the Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the Taſting, &amp; the Touching.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The ſame ſort of Prayer, a Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may vſe vpon the Rules of his Order and Office. And euerie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, may eaſilie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitablie apply the ſame to his Eſtate and Office.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:12413:46"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Vocall Prayer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VOcall Prayer is two-fould; The on Publique, to wit, the Canonicall houres and Pſalmes: The other Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, as the Office of our Ladie, the Bedes, &amp; and the like. The firſt, is of Obligation: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is often made of deuotion, and ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes alſo of Obligation, as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is enioyned for
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12413:47"/> Penannce by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſar, or elſe by Statute or Vowe. Both to the one, and the other, we are to bring due prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration &amp; attention, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing three things.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. At the beginning, or before hee beginne Vocall Prayer, to retire himſelfe a part, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into himſelfe, &amp; lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp his hart to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, to offer vnto him this worke, to his honour and glorie, beſeeching him to aſſiſt vs. &amp;c. And to this ende
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12413:47"/> may ſaye; <hi>Actiones no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stras,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In the progreſſe of this Prayer, hee muſt doe two thinges; The one, to promou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e the wordes diſtinctly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making ouer-much haſte; Theother, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as at the <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> of the Pſalmes, and at the ende of euerie ten of the Beades) to renew his attention, that is to ſay, to rectifie himſelfe, if he hath bene diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to goe forward with a new deuotion.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:12413:48"/>3. Hauing finiſhed, to render thankes, &amp; craue pardon for the faultes which one hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in praying.</p>
                     <p>An excellent forme of Vocall Prayer, is this: To recite our Lordes Prayer, (and the ſame is to bee vnderſtood, of all other prayer) faire &amp; ſoftly, word by word, &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing each word, to pauſe or employ ſo much time, as the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall breath of a man can laſt, in ſuch ſort or wiſe, that the wordes do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12413:48"/> or march together, with the ſeuerall brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things: prouided, that whileſt on pronounceth the wordes outwardlie, he muſt inwardlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſignification of the worde, or the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of the perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>age, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on ſpeaketh or our owne vilitie, one may ſtay himſelfe, praying af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this faſhion, as long as one wil, reciting ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie other Prayers, or repeating the ſame.</p>
                     <p>This ſorte of Prayer is verie good, eaſie,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12413:49"/> full of deuotion, &amp; not ſubiect to diſtraction; &amp; ought euerie day to be put in practiſe, not in ſaying the Breuiarie, or the Beades (for it would take vp too much time) and ſaying at the leaſt a <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Aue,</hi> and that eſpecialie at the end of Meditation, after wee haue made the Mentall Colloquie.</p>
                     <p>When one is in iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and euerie time that one cannot conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently Meditate, then may one ſerue himſelfe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12413:49"/> of this ſorte of Prayer, the which is very eaſie, and may be made euen in going.</p>
                     <p>The Supplications of Holie Church, which wee call the Litanies, is a kinde of vocall Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, very ancient, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie proper, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth the ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Saints, Obſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all ſorts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, for our ſelues, &amp; for our neighbours, quick, and dead, and for all eſtates: and therfore all Chriſtians ought of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12413:50"/> recite them.</p>
                     <p>The Prayers alſo which we call Collects, are verie good, deuout, and holie, whereof one muſt ſerue himſelfe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when one will demande ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar grace, or praye for ſome neceſſity, which preſenteth it ſelfe, as, for Peace, for the Sicke, for thoſe that are in voyage, and the like: and are to be found, at the end of the Miſſal, and in the Office of our Ladie.</p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:12413:50"/>
                     <p>Likewiſe it is good in prayinge vnto ſome Saint, to preſent vnto Almightie God, and to recite the proper Prayer or Collect of the ſame Saint: and, if hee haue not a proper Collect, to take the Common.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the Beades.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AMongſt all other Prayers, as well Vocall, as others; the firſt and principall is, the <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12413:51"/> after this, the Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For this cauſe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſundrie others) the Beades, or Crowne of our Ladie, is an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forme of Praier, as being compoſed of theſe two Prayers.</p>
                     <p>Now to recite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutlie and fruitfullie the Beades: Firſt one muſt obſerue the three precepts before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, touching Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prayer.</p>
                     <p>Beſides this one muſt (whilſt one reciteth the Aue Maries) haue his
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12413:51"/> thoughts fixed vpon ſome good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome thinge, as vpon Death, vpon Hell, vpon Heauen, his ſinnes, and principallie vpon the myſteries of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which are contayned in the life of our B. Lord, and of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>For this cauſe or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, B. Saint Dominike choſe fifteene Myſteries of the Roſarie, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole worlde, to contemplate and conſider them in ſaying
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12413:52"/> the Beades. Wee muſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue them &amp; know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by heart, the which is very eaſie.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Mysteries of the Roſarie.</head>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Fiue are called Ioyfull.</head>
                           <p>1. The Annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation of the Angell. 2. The Viſitation of our Ladie. 3. The Natiuitie of our Lord. 4. The Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in the Temple. 5. How he was founde diſputinge amongſt the Doctors.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Fiue are called Dolefull.</head>
                           <p>1. The Prayer in the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:12413:52"/> Garden. 2. The whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge at the Pillar. 3. The crowninge with Thornes. 4. The cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Croſſe. 5. The Crucifying.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                           <head>Fiue are called glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</head>
                           <p>1. The Reſurrection of our Lord. 2. His Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion. 3. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the holy Ghoſt. 4. The Aſſump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ion of our Ladie. 5. Her Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
                           <p>The practiſe &amp; faſhion to ſay the Beades vpon theſe fifteene Miſteries,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12413:53"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="103" facs="tcp:12413:53"/>
                              <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                                 <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <pb n="104" facs="tcp:12413:54"/> is double, or two fould. The one is, vpon one <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> &amp; ten <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> to conſider one myſterie, that is to ſaye, whilſt one ſaith one <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and ten <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> alwaies to haue our thought vpon that myſterie; As, at the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of the Incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to thinke vpon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, vpon our Ladie, and vpon their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>The other is, vpon each myſterie, to ſay on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie one <hi>Aue Marie,</hi> that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12413:54"/> is to ſaye, recite one <hi>Aue Marie,</hi> conſidering the Annuntiation, another conſidering the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, and to make the round of theſe fifteene, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times, as till all the Beades be finiſhed.</p>
                           <p>One may alſo collect fiftie or ſixtie myſteries, and principall workes of the life of our Lorde, from the Annuntiation, vnto the Aſcention; and vpon each one, to ſay an <hi>Aue Marie:</hi> allwaies remembring to ſay a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12413:55"/> 
                              <hi>Pater noster,</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of euery ten.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>A forme of Meditating, in ſaying the Beades.</head>
                        <p>There are ſundrie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manners of ſaying the Beades, wee will content our ſelues here to ſet downe one other onely, the which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in conſideringe our ſinnes; and the foure laſt thinges of Man, and is this.</p>
                        <p>One muſt imagine, that the Beades which one hath in his hande, are coloured, and that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12413:55"/> theſe colours repreſent vnto vs, the matter which we deſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, in recitinge the Beades.</p>
                        <p>To imagine the firſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graines, which are on the Beades, as if they were of diuers colours, white, black, red, green, yellow, tawny, &amp;c. The ſecond, of a pale colour. The third of a red co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. The fourth, of a blak colour. And the fift, of the colour of gould.</p>
                        <p>That is to ſay in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt ten, which
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:12413:56"/> are of diuers coloure, to reduce into memorie, the multitude &amp; diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of thy ſinnes, which thou haſt committed in thy whole life, crauinge pardon of Almightie God, by the interceſſion of our B. Ladie.</p>
                        <p>In ſaying the ſecond ten, which are of Pale colour, to represe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto thy ſelfe the memory of Death.</p>
                        <p>In ſayinge the third ten, to thincke of the terrible day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:12413:56"/>
                        <p>In ſaying the fourth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the paines of Hell.</p>
                        <p>And in the fifth of the glorie of Heauen.</p>
                        <p>And who ſo would ſaie in this ſort, the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſixtie three <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> let him adde to the ſixt ten, of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Siluer, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his thought, the puritie of our B. Ladie.</p>
                        <p>Thus to ſay the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, is Vocall Prayer, to the which one may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firablie adioyne Mental Prayer and Meditation, at the beginning &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12413:57"/> of euery te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reſting himſelfe ſometime; to meditate ſome miſtery, and to pray Mentally.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Iaculatorie Prayers.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SAint Auguſtine <hi>(in his Epist. 121. ad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum)</hi> calleth Iauclato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Prayers, certaine briefe Prayers and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, or dartinges of the ſpirit, into Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God; as for example in ſaying: <hi>Deus in adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torium meum intende.</hi> All
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12413:57"/> ſuch Prayers may bee both Mentall and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tall, inuoking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly Almighty God, vnto our ſuccour, and pondering in ſpirit, the meaning and contents of the ſame ſentence; <hi>Incline to myne aide, o God.</hi> Vocall, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinge with the mouth the ſame wordes, either in Latin, or in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar tongue.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Iaculatorie Prayers are very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, as well to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainevs in continual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12413:58"/> and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, as to accompliſh that which our Lord hath ſaid: <hi>Pray alwaies.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell when we heare ſay that S. Bartholomew praied a hundred times a day, and a hundred ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the night; Alſo S. Martha, and S. Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus Abbot, and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie other Saints, who wholly gaue themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to Prayer; for this is moſt eaſie (ſo farre off is it from being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble)
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:12413:58"/> by the meanes of theſe Iaculatory, Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, or Vocall prayers, eſpecially, ſith Prayer is nothing elſe, then an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuation of the minde vnto Almightie God, which may be done an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred times an houre; and our Lordes Prayer, was expreſly giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs ſo briefe, to the ende, that euery Chriſtian might preſent it to God a hundred times a day, if ſo he will.</p>
                     <p>Euerie ſpirituall man then, ought to take the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12413:59"/> paines to accuſtome him ſelfe to theſe Iacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorie Prayers. And to remember him ſelfe, a good meanes it is, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie time that one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the clocke, from the Morning, vntill the Euening, to make a Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatory Prayer, both by heart and mouth, being all alone. Whereunto, alſo would greatly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, that euerie one doe ſelect ſome ſentences, moſt pleaſinge vnto them, taking them prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallie, out of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:12413:59"/> Pſalmes, and to take each day, one for practiſe.</p>
                     <p>And for as much as the <hi>Pater noster</hi> is truely our dailie bread; it ſhall be very good to take for Iaculatorie Prayers, the ſeuen Petitions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the ſame, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie day one; As one Sundaye, to repeate manie times, both by heart and mouth, <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificetur nomen tuum.</hi> One Munday, <hi>Adueniat regnum tuum:</hi> and ſo of others.</p>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:12413:60"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Excellencie of our Lords Prayer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And note I beſeeche you, the perfection and excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of this diuine Prayer, how the ſame fitteth all ſorts of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to wit, Mentall, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Mixt, Iaculatorie, and Meditation.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The <hi>Parer noſter</hi> may ſerue for Mentall Prayer, ſaying it in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and preſenting to God, all that which is contained in the ſame, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the other,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. For Vocal Prayer,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12413:60"/> recitinge the ſame with the mouth.</p>
                     <p>For mixt Prayer, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge it firſt with the heart, and after with the mouth.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. For Iaculatorie prayers, as we haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely ſaid.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Fiftlie, for Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for one may me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate the ſame: yea, it is a moſt excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of meditation, as ſhal be feene hereafter.</p>
                     <p>Of all theſe manner of Prayers, the one are more proper for ſome
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12413:61"/> perſons, the other more proper for others; yea, one and the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at one time ſhall be more apt to vſe one manner of Prayer, and at another time ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, accordinge to the diſpoſition of the ſoule or the bodie. As when any one is wearie, or elſe is not well at eaſe, and ſhall be indiſpoſed to make long Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then may hee moſt helpe him ſelfe by Vocall, or by Mixt Prayer.</p>
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:12413:61"/>
                     <p>In voyage, a foote, or a horſe-backe, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or Mixt prayers; are moſt proper and moſt eaſie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of Spirituall Reading.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>LEt vs preſuppoſe that which is true, the readinge of holie bookes, to be a thinge exceedinge profitable, and a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: whence we ſee, that all thoſe who haue
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12413:62"/> loued, and doe loue Prayer, haue embraced with like affection ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall reading; we will here therefore onelie ſhewe that which is to be obſerued, to reade with profite.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, what bookes we ought to reade. Firſt of all, the Holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (for ſuch as ſhall by their Spirituall Father be iudged fit to read it) eſpecially the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; the Epiſtles of S. Paule; the Epiſtles of S.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:12413:62"/> Iames; and the firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of S. Iohn.</p>
                     <p>Of the Ould Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the bookes of Iob; the three bookes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon; the Prouerbes; Eccleſiaſticus, &amp; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes.</p>
                     <p>After the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to reade other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bookes, but the beſt and moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt, whereof we will make a roule or Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
                     <p>2. Each one ought to reade thoſe bookes, which are moſt to his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12413:63"/> guſt, and which he hath experimented to haue brought him moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. And therefore he ought to proue diuers, and then to houlde him ſelfe to that which hee findeth fitteſt for him.</p>
                     <p>3. Not to deceaue him ſelfe in the election of ſuch bookes, let him aske aduiſe of his ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father.</p>
                     <p>4. He muſt not be inconſtant, and nowe read one booke, and nowe another, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12413:63"/> foorth one booke, from one ende to the other. True it is, that ſometimes one may change to take away diſtaſte, or that a man doth ſometime finde himſelfe more diſpoſed to reade one booke, then another; and then to continue to reade the other which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne.</p>
                     <p>5. It is verye meete to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme his reading, vnto his Meditation, that is to ſay, to reade the ſame matter, that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12413:64"/> one doth Meditate as much as is poſſible.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The ſecond,</hi> how one muſt reade. 1. He muſt haue a right intention, and not to reade vpon curioſitie, or for deſire of knowledge, or for the elegancy of the ſtile; but to ſtirre vp him ſelfe to deuotion, and to profite in ſpirite.</p>
                     <p>2. He muſt not read in poſte-haſte, but ſoftly and deuoutly, chewing the wordes which one readeth.</p>
                     <p>3. Meeting with any
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:12413:64"/> notable and profitable thinge, not to paſſe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to ſtay himſelf, and to ponder it, adding moreouer ſome little prayer.</p>
                     <p>4. The moſt worthy ſentences, and thinges moſt profitable, to lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne them by heart, to be able to recount them, and to ſerue him ſelfe of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The third,</hi> touchinge the time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one muſt reade.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Firſt, when the ſoule hath appetite to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:12413:65"/> reade, and enclineth thereto.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. When a man fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe arride &amp; drie in deuotion.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. On holy daies more then on other dayes.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Before, or after Communion, or cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the ſacred Maſſe.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Sometimes it is good to reade before. Prayer and Meditation, to excite himſelfe to deuotion, and to finde matter, whereon to Meditate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:12413:65"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Such Spirituall Bookes as are moſt profitable for all perſons.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A Little booke inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, Gerſon, or Thomas a Kempis, of the followinge of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>The life of Chriſt, by S. Bonauenture.</p>
                     <p>The workes of F. Lewes of Granade; namely, his Spirituall Doctrine or Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12413:66"/> His Memoriall of a Chriſtian life. His Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations. His Treatiſe of the loue of God, and of his Benefits.</p>
                     <p>The contempt of the worlde.</p>
                     <p>The Liues of Saints.</p>
                     <p>The Meditations of Father Loart, vpon the Miſteries of the Roſary. His Chriſtian Exerciſe. And his Meditations vpon the Paſſion.</p>
                     <p>Comfort in T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by Sir Thomas Moore:</p>
                     <p>The Epiſtle of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12413:66"/> by Father South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. And his Rules of good life.</p>
                     <p>The Paradiſe of the ſoule by Albertus Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</p>
                     <p>The miracles of our Ladie of Loretto, of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim, &amp; of other places.</p>
                     <p>Father Fuluius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drotius, of the frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the B. Sacrament. And his Meditations vpon the Paſſion.</p>
                     <p>Father Brunoes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. And his Abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement.</p>
                     <p>The Societie of the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12413:67"/> Roſarie.</p>
                     <p>The Introduction to a deuout life, by Francis Sales, biſhop of Geneua.</p>
                     <p>Father Points Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
                     <p>Father Parſons Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Directorie.</p>
                     <p>A briefe Collection, concerning the Loue of God towardes man, found amongſt his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, who compoſed the Ieſus Pſalter.</p>
                     <p>Wholſome and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Doctrine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge the 7. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by the Reuerend
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:12413:67"/> F. in God, Thomas, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Lincolne.</p>
                     <p>The booke intituled, Six ſpirituall bookes, full of marueilous pietie and deuotion.</p>
                     <p>The ſacred Myſterie of the Flagellation of our Lord and Sauiour.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Others, particularlie for Religious perſons, beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the aforeſaid.</head>
                        <p>The Epiſtle of Ieſus Chriſt, to the faithfull ſoule.</p>
                        <p>A briefe Methode, howe to ſerue God in a perfect ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, by F. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo.</p>
                        <pb n="131" facs="tcp:12413:68"/>
                        <p>The Spiritual Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict.</p>
                        <p>A Treatiſe of Mental Prayer, by F. Molina, Carthuſian Monke.</p>
                        <p>The Mirror of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by F. Lucas Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelli: And him vpon the life of our B. Ladie.</p>
                        <p>A Spiritual Exerciſe, written by F. William Perin, Prior, and Friar Preacher, of great S. Bartholomes in Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</p>
                        <p>With ſundrie others (all of them to be found in our Engliſh tongue)
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12413:68"/> which the Ghoſtlie Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall iudge to be moſt conuenient and proper for euery perſon.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE haue ſaid at the beginning, that two thinges are neceſſarie to make vs to Meditate, to wit, the <hi>Matter,</hi> and the <hi>Manner:</hi> whereof we muſt now treate in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to the ende to ayde euery one, both in
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12413:69"/> the one and the other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The matter of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is to ſay, what things one must Meditate and conſider.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Death, Iudgement, the paines of Hell, and the glorie of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</item>
                        <item>The vanitye of the world, and the miſeries of this preſent life.</item>
                        <item>The ſinnes wee haue committed in our whole life.</item>
                        <item>The life death, &amp; Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord, and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Euchariſt.</item>
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:12413:69"/>
                        <item>The Benefites of God.</item>
                        <item>The life of our Ladie, and of the Saintes.</item>
                        <item>The vertues.</item>
                        <item>The booke of the Creatures.</item>
                        <item>The Perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of God which we cal Atributes.</item>
                        <item>Al the holie Scripture, eſpecially, the holy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the Pſalmes.</item>
                        <item>Our Lordes Prayer, as alſo the Creede of the Apoſtles, is verye good and profitable to Meditate.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Al which is contained in the Chriſtian Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12413:70"/> of Catechiſme, may likewiſe ſerue for matter of Meditation.</p>
                     <p>One muſt meditate often, vpon the ende for which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this worlde, for it is the foundation of our ſaluation &amp; perfection.</p>
                     <p>It is good to confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ones ſelfe to Holy Church, and to followe her traces: as, One ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne daies, to conſider the Miſteries, which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are propoſed vnto vs.</p>
                     <p>One the Feaſtes of Saints, to conſider their
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12413:70"/> life, death, vertues, and moſt remarkable actes, and the glorie which they haue acquired.</p>
                     <p>In Aduent, to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the myſterie of the Incarnation, or on the life of our Lord.</p>
                     <p>In Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, one may take euery day, the Goſpel of the day for Meditation.</p>
                     <p>The matters moſt proper to Meditate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sundaies, are the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our Lord. Our Reſurrection and beatitude, figured by the Sunday. The Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12413:71"/> of God. And the Goſpel of the day. And as there are foure Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies in the month, one may Meditate euery Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, one of the four mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters afore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aid.</p>
                     <p>On the dayes of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, to Meditate v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the holy Euchariſt, or vpon the Paſſion of our Lord.</p>
                     <p>On Fridaie, vpon the Paſſion of our Lord.</p>
                     <p>And on Saterdaye, ſomthing of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>When one hath heard ſome Sermon, or
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12413:71"/> Exhortation, the ſame daye, or on the morrow to repeate the ſame, and to make his Meditation thereupon.</p>
                     <p>Beſides this, the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſon, the Prieſt, and euery one, ought often to Meditate vpon his vocation, vow, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, eſtate and office.</p>
                     <p>Euerie one alſo ought often to Meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the vertue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he hath greateſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie: and vpon the imperfection, whereof he moſt deſireth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12413:72"/> him ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>And euen as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die doth addict it ſelfe moſt willinglie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and would ofteneſt eate of thoſe meates, which beſt doe like it: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ſoule ought oftneſt to chew &amp; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate thoſe matters, wherein ſhee findeth moſt taſte and ſpirituall profite; For it is true in thinges ſpirituall, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporall, as the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians ſay. <hi>Quod ſapit nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trit.</hi> That which reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, nouriſheth.</p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:12413:72"/>
                     <p>Finally, as touching the matter of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thou muſt obſerue three other points. The firſt, that at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of euerie Moneth, and of euery week, thou oughteſt to be diligent, to foreſee, and prepare the matter, that thou entendeſt on the month or weeke enſuing.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond, that when one hath begun to Meditate ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, each daie, if ſome iuſt occaſion preſent it ſelfe to Meditate ſome
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12413:73"/> other thinge, as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Solemnitie, &amp;c. For that day to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt it, and to leaue the matter one hath in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d; and on the morrowe to returne &amp; goe forward, as before.</p>
                     <p>The third, that all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be good, from month to month, and from weeke to weeke, to take ſome matter, to meditate one ſo manie daies as it ſhall laſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe, one may alſo euerie daye meditate diuers matters. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12413:73"/> that the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, are theſe foure; the laſt Endings of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Death, Iudgement, Hel, and Heauen, the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord, our ſinnes, and the Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Almightie God, one may oftimes, and within one weeke Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate them all, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame order, and in this ſort.</p>
                     <p>Monday, of Death.</p>
                     <p>Tueſday, of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                     <p>Wenſday, of the paines of Hell.</p>
                     <p>Thurſday, of the glory
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12413:74"/> of Heauen.</p>
                     <p>Fridaie, of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Lord.</p>
                     <p>Saturdaie, of our Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
                     <p>Sundaie, of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of Almighty God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Diuers manners of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting diuers things. Manners of Meditatinge the foure last ends of a Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe may euery day Meditate one of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12413:74"/> theſe foure thinges, Death, Iudgement, the paines of Hell, and the glorie of Heauen.</p>
                     <p>One may alſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> each of theſe foure endes, make su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Vpon Death, one may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider principally theſe points.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. That one muſt nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des die.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. When, where, and how, no man knoweth.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That in Death, one leaueth all behinde him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Another manner.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. To conſider the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:12413:75"/> thinges which goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Death, as ſicknes, phiſicke, dolors and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Vnction.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The thinges that accompanie it, as are the grieuous paines of the bodie, the loſſe of the ſenſes, the waxing cold, the paines of the ſoule, the temptations, the viſions, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Thoſe which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, as Buriall, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Iudgement.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Another Manner.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. That death is very dreadfull.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <pb n="147" facs="tcp:12413:75"/>2. That one muſt feare it, deſpiſe, and deſire it.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That one muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe to dy wel.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Vpon the latter iudgement, theſe things principally are to be conſidered.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. The dreadful ſignes that ſhall goe before it.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Renouation of the world.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The Reſurrection of all the children of Adam, at the ſound of the Trumpet.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. The maieſtie of the Iudge, aſſiſted with all his Court.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <pb n="148" facs="tcp:12413:76"/>5. The rendring of account, and the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the bookes of al mens conſciences.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. The double ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: &amp; each one ought to know the wordes, &amp; to conſider them.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. The executions of them.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Diuers manners of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating, vpon the Glorie of the bleſſed.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="1">1. One is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, 1. the place. 2. the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, 3. the actions of the Bleſſed.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Another, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, 1. The goods of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12413:76"/> 2. The goods of the bodie. 3. The Exteriour.</p>
                        <p>2. Another to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three douaries and Perfections of the ſoule, which are, viſion, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and euerlaſtinge Enioying.</p>
                        <p>4. Another to conſider the foure douaries and perfections of the Body, Impaſſibilitie, Claritie, Agilitie, Subtilitie.</p>
                        <p>5. Another, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Ioy, which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of the fiue Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes ſhall haue.</p>
                        <p>Another faſhion is,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12413:77"/> to conſider the ſeauen points following, in one or more Meditations.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Point, to conſider the excellency of the Place, to wit, the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Beautie, and the Riches of heauen.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The Beatitude of the Bodie, how it ſhall be endued with foure excellent qualities to wit, that it ſhal be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Impaſſible, moſt bright-ſhininge, moſt Agile or nimble, and (as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) ſpirituall, that is
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12413:77"/> to ſay, which can paſſe quite through other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (as through a ſtone walle) without let or impediment.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The Beatitude of the Soule, as, the great wiſedome, ſeeing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God face to face, and all thinges in him. The moſt ardent loue of God, and his neighbour. The Ioye and Contentment, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinite.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. The Companie of the Bleſſed, to wit, of all the Angels, of all the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:12413:78"/> Saints, and of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Mother of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. To confider the Actions and Exerciſes of the Bleſſed; which are, perpetuall Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, Ioye, Loue, Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, Paſſetime, &amp; Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Almighty God; Magdalene alone, and no Martha, no externall buſineſſe, or office of the world.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. No euill, and all that is good, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the good things, and the euills of this
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12413:78"/> world, to aſcend to the conſideration of thoſe aboue.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. How long all the ſame ſhall endure: for all eternitie without ende.</p>
                        <p n="8">8. Another faſhion is, to conſider, that on euery ſide, they ſhall enioy moſt vnſpeakable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
                        <p>1. The Ioye that the Bleſſed ſhall haue in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houlding on high, the moſt ſacred mother of Almightie God, our Lord and Redeemer,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:12413:79"/> and all the holie Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. 2. Rounde about him, the aforeſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the place. 3. In him ſelfe, the beatitude both of ſoule and body.</p>
                        <p>4. Beneath him, the world, Limbo &amp; Hell.</p>
                        <p>Another, to conſider that in that place there is no manner of euill, and is all manner of good; makinge two diſcourſes, one vpon the euills, another vpon the good things.</p>
                        <p>Touching the paines
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:12413:79"/> of the damned, there are as manye manners to Meditate them, as the glorye of the Bleſſed: there needs no more, but to change the good things into euill.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Manners of Meditating, whereby to attaine the knowledge of ones ſelfe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>1. THe firſt is, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the time paſt, preſent, and to come, as S. Bernard tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:12413:80"/> in ſundrie places, ſaying. O man thincke, firſt, what thou haſt bene: ſecond, what thou art; third, what thou ſhalt be.</p>
                     <p>Or thus; Firſt, from whence come I? Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Where am I? Third, whether goe I?</p>
                     <p>Or thus; what is the entrie of man into the world. Second, what his abode. Third, what his departure.</p>
                     <p>2. To conſider (as the ſame Doctor ſaieth, lib. 2. <hi>De conſid.)</hi> 1. Thy
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:12413:80"/> ſelfe, who and what thou art. 2. The things that are vnderneath thee, Limbo, Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and Hel. 3. The thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee, the world, the Creatures, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels. 4. The things that are aboue thee, the glory of Paradiſe.</p>
                     <p>3. To conſider foure other thinges, according to the counſaile of the ſame Saint Bernard <hi>(De inferiore capite</hi> 65. 1.) What thou art by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. What thou haſt bin
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:12413:81"/> by ſinne. 3. what thou maieſt be by the grace of Almightie God.</p>
                     <p>4. To conſider the words of Moyſes (Deut. 32.) O that men would conſider the things that are Paſt (the euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, the time loſt, and Ieſus Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ied.) The Preſent (the benefits of God, the vanitie of the worlde, the breuitie of this life, and the difficultie to be ſaued.) And fore-ſee things to come (Death particular, generall Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:12413:81"/> Hell, and the glorie of heauen.)</p>
                     <p>5. To conſider the four cauſes of man. 1. The cauſe Efficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, who made him, to wit God, 2. The materiall cauſe; the body made of earth, 3. The formal cauſe, the ſoule, the image of God. 4. The finall cauſe, wherefore man was made, to witt, for eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall beatitude.</p>
                     <p>6. To conſider him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, according to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie eſtates. 1. In as much as man. 2. In as
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:12413:82"/> much as a Chriſtian. 3. In as much as Religious, a Prieſt, or of any other eſtate or condition.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>The manner how to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſinnes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe firſt is, to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate his proper ſinnes, to know them, and to haue true ſorrow and contrition for them: deuiding them into cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine points and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, as, to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. 1. Their multitude.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:12413:82"/> 2. Their grieuouſneſſe. 3. The damages they bringe with them. For the multitude, one may obſerue ſome order: as, to conſider the yeares of our life, in ſuch, or ſuch a place; and in ſuch companie &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Item, the ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by thoughts, by wordes, by workes, and by omiſſion.</p>
                     <p>Item, the ſinnes I haue committed againſt God, againſt my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and againſt my ſelfe; And note, that in
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:12413:83"/> conſidering his ſinnes, he muſt not ſtaye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vpon the ſinne of the fleſh, and of choler, but verie little.</p>
                     <p>Note alſo, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fit and profitable for a ſpirituall man, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh in him ſelfe, the memorie of his life paſt, and ſometimes to make one whole Meditation vpon the ſame, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to paſſe it ouer in praying and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in a quarter, or half an houre, diuidinge it into as many partes, as
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12413:83"/> the places are, wherein he hath dwelt; in the ſame faſhion that we ſhall by and by, ſpeak of the life of our Lord.</p>
                     <p>The other faſhion is, to conſider the Sinne in it ſelfe, to conceaue a hatred and horror of the ſame, meditatinge. 1. How much ſinne is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſinge to God, and wholie contrary vnto him.</p>
                     <p>2. How much hurt it bringeth to the man who committeth it, and ſometimes to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:12413:84"/> alſo: to ſoule, to bodie, to honour, and to his goods, or ſubſtance.</p>
                     <p>3. How manie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages it bringeth to the whole world, and how exceedinge grieuouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie Almighty God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies chaſtiſed it: recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, as of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels them ſelues, and of mankinde.</p>
                     <p>Another maner is, to take the ſeauen capitall Sinnes, which ſome call Mortall, and euerie day to meditate one in
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12413:84"/> forme following.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Vpon Sunday, Pride.</item>
                        <item>Mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day, Couetouſnes.</item>
                        <item>Tueſday, Luxurie.</item>
                        <item>Wenſday, Enuie.</item>
                        <item>Thurſday, Gluttonie.</item>
                        <item>Fridaie, Anger.</item>
                        <item>Saturday, Slout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Vpon euerie one of which, one muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe three points. 1. Howe much ſuch a ſinne diſpleaſeth God. 2. How much it hurteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 3. How many times I haue offended God by ſuch a ſinne, &amp; his bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: and each of theſe
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:12413:85"/> points may be made double, as for example.</p>
                     <p>1. Howe much this vice diſpleaſeth God, &amp; how doeth pleaſe him the contrarie vertue. 2. Howe much this vice hurteth man, and howe profitable is the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vertue. 3. How much I haue offended by this vice, and how farre off I haue bene, &amp; am from the oppoſite vertue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:12413:85"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>Manners how to Meditate the whole life of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing alſo his Paſsion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe firſt manner is, to Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate the principall myſteries, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie daie one, from the Annuntiation, vnto the Aſcenſion, as S. Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, F. Lewes of Granade. &amp; F. Vincent Bruno haue done.</p>
                     <p>2. One may deuide
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:12413:86"/> the whole life of our Lord into ſeauen parts, and finiſh them in one weeke, as Saint Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture doeth.</p>
                     <p>3. One may diuide the whole life of our Lord, into ten parts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ten pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where hee hath dwelte in this worlde, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering what he hath done, and endured for thee in euery place.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In his Mothers wombe, nine Moneths.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In the Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, or in Bethelem, fourty dayes.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="169" facs="tcp:12413:86"/>3. In Egypt, about ſeauen yeares.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In Nazareth, more then two and twentie yeares.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. In the Deſert, fourty daies, &amp; forty nightes.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Preaching in Iurie, and in Galilee, about three yeares and a halfe.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. In grieuous paine and torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, one whole daie.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Vpon the Croſſe, three houres.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. In the Sepulchre, and in Limbo, fourty houres.</p>
                     <p n="10">
                        <pb n="170" facs="tcp:12413:87"/>10. Here in earth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Reſurrection, fourty daies.</p>
                     <p>In this maner, within one houre, yea halfe an houre, one may medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the whole life of our Lord Ieſus, pauſing a litle vpon euery one of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parts, or points: the which is very eaſie, and very profitable. One may likewiſe make vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ten partes, ten Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, or more, or leſſe, as one wil himſelf.</p>
                     <p>4. One may likewiſe diuide the whole life of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:12413:87"/> our Lord, into three partes, to wit, his entrie into this worlde, his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding here, and his iſſue or departing. How hee entred, what hee did whilſt he dwelt here. And in what manner he went out of it: as S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas hath diuided it; And vpon each of theſe parts to make one, or more Meditations.</p>
                     <p>5. One may alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende it in three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther generall partes or members, as S. Bernard ſaith (in his <hi>Summe:)</hi>
                        <pb n="172" facs="tcp:12413:88"/> conſidering, what he hath ſaid, what hee hath done, and what hee hath endured. <hi>Dixit mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, fecit mira, pertulit du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> He ſpake many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, did maruellous things, endured paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things: and vpon each of theſe points, to make one, or more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations.</p>
                     <p>Wee will ſtay no longer vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe points, not to be ouer-lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: for if he be a little exerciſed in theſe affaires, he may
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:12413:88"/> forme of him ſelfe, that which here is ſaid: or if he haue need, lett him aske aduiſe of his ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father.</p>
                     <p>6. One may likewiſe do in this manner, to wit, to meditate the fifteene myſteries of the Roſarie, making v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euerie one, one or more Meditations.</p>
                     <p>7. One may take one of the foure Goſpels, and meditate the ſame, from one ende to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Or of the whole foure, to mak one <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſaron,</hi>
                        <pb n="174" facs="tcp:12413:89"/> thoſe who can performe it.</p>
                     <p>8. In the litle Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme of Caniſius, there are ſeuen very excellent Meditations, each one containinge fiue points, drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foorth of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, Life, and Paſſion of our Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>Maners of Meditating the Paſsion of our Lord.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. THe firſt manner is, to beginne
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:12413:89"/> from the laſt Supper, and euerie day to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate one Myſterie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his death and burial, followinge the text of one Euangeliſt, or of all the foure togeather: as S. Bonauenture Loar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, and Coſterus haue done.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To deuide the Paſſion of our Lord into ſeauen partes, and to meditate it in one weeke, as S. Bonauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; Lewis of Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado hath done.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. One may make as
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:12413:90"/> many Meditations, as there are places wherin he ſuffered, makinge each day, as a Station in one place. 1. In the place of the laſt ſupper, where he waſhed his Diſciples feete, and inſtituted the B. Sacrament. 2. In the Garden, where hee contriſtated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſweat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly a bloodie ſweate. 3. Before An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, where he receaued a grieuous blow on the face. 4. Before Cay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas where he was ſpit
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:12413:90"/> on, and blinde-foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. 5. In the houſe of Pilate, where beinge falſlie accuſed, he vſed wounderfull modeſtie, patience and ſilence. 6. In the houſe of Herod, where hee was deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, clothed in a white garment, and reputed for a foole. 7. Againe, before Pilate, where he was nakedly ſcourged, and condemned to die. 8. In the way towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Caluarie, bearinge his heauie Croſſe. 9. His death and Paſſion,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:12413:91"/> vpon the ſame moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. One may medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in one weeke, the ſeuen words which our B. Lord and Sauiour ſpake, hanging three houres aliue vpon the Croſſe: which each good Chriſtian ought to haue by hart.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Father forgiue them, they know not what they doe.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To the Thiefe; Verely I ſaye vnto thee, this day thou ſhalt be with mee in Paradiſe.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="179" facs="tcp:12413:91"/>3. To his ſorrowfull Mother; woman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould thy ſonne: and to Saint Iohn, behould thy mother.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. My God my God, why haſt thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mee.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. I thirſt.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. All is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Father into thy hands I commende my ſpirit.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. One may chooſe out of the whole Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, about a dozen my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, whereon to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, as F. Fuluiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drotius
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:12413:92"/> hath done.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Another maner is, to meditate three thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or three ſeuerall ſortes of paines, to wit; that which our Sauiour ſuffered in foule in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and in his honour: and vpon each of theſe three points, to make one, or more Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and all this may be drawen foorth of the holy Ghoſpell, or foorth of ſome booke that treateth of this ſubiect.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. One may likewiſe
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:12413:92"/> Meditate foure thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Who he is that ſuffereth. What things he ſuffereth. For whom. And how he ſuffereth, makinge vpon euerie of theſe points, one or more conſiderations; The which foure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, ought alſo to bee made in all the Meditations, which one maketh vpon the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And albeit that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of theſe maners ſeem to be points of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet are they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers waies and faſhions
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:12413:93"/> of Meditating.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. One may Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Paſſion of our Lorde, by diuers waies, to drawe from thence diuers affections, as Saint Bonauenture hath taught in his booke, of the darte of diuine loue, and after him, Denis the Charter-houſe Monke, Granado, Loartus, and others.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. By way of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, conſidering the grieuouſneſſe of his paines.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By way of Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:12413:93"/> conſidering that he is dead for our ſinnes.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. By way of Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to imitate and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his example.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. By way of Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, conſidering the greatneſſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. By way of Loue, conſidering the Loue, which he hath ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. By way of Hope, ſith that he is deade to ſaue vs.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. By way of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, aſtoniſhing him
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:12413:94"/> ſelfe, at ſo great a loue and bountie.</p>
                     <p>And this may be done, in one only weeke, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating the Paſſion of our Lord, euery day by one of theſe waies.</p>
                     <p>Item, at each point or Meditation of the Paſſion, one muſt excite in him ſelfe ſome one, or more of the ſaid Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>Maners of meditating vpon the holy Eucharist.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe may meditate a great number of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:12413:94"/> thinges vpon the holy Euchariſt.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Historie.</head>
                        <p>How he eate the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Lambe with his Apoſtles.</p>
                        <p>How he waſhed their feete.</p>
                        <p>How he inſtituted the B. Sacrament, and did communicate them.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The names.</head>
                        <p>Euchariſtie, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, abſoluement, Communion, Sacrifice, Bread, Viaticum.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The figures.</head>
                        <p>The bread and wine
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:12413:95"/> of Melchiſedeck, the Paſchal Lambe, Manna, and the bread of Elias.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The Cauſes wherefore it was instituted.</head>
                        <p>For a memorie of his Paſſion.</p>
                        <p>To ſhew vs his loue.</p>
                        <p>For foode of our ſoule.</p>
                        <p>To ſerue vs for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
                        <p>For pledge of Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>The effects or fruits of the Sacrament.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. It worketh in the ſoule, all that which the bread doth in the body;
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:12413:95"/> it nouriſheth it, it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it life, it fortifies it againſt her enemies, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteth it, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth it with ioy &amp;c.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. illuminateth the vnderſtanding, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames the hart.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. It vniteth and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porateth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with God.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. It augmenteth all the vertues, Faith, Hope, and ſo of others.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. It changeth a man, &amp; maketh him another by amendement of his life and maners.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. It rendreth a man
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:12413:96"/> as it were aſſured of his ſaluation.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. It giueth in this world the grace of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and in the other, glorie.</p>
                        <p>One may alſo meditate vpon the Antiphone, <hi>O ſacrum conuiuium,</hi> the which containeth ſixe partes or branches.</p>
                        <p>O ſacred banquet.</p>
                        <p>In which Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued.</p>
                        <p>The memory of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is called to minde.</p>
                        <p>The ſoule is repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with grace.</p>
                        <pb n="189" facs="tcp:12413:96"/>
                        <p>And a pledge of future glorie is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs.</p>
                        <p>Moreouer, one may Meditate vpon theſe foure circumſtances. Who he is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. To whome he commeth. How he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. And wherefore he commeth.</p>
                        <p>Likewiſe one may Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; endeuour, of him which is to receaue it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>How one must Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue it.</head>
                        <p>Two things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie before we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:12413:97"/> it; Puritie, and deſire.</p>
                        <p>Two in receauing it; Humilitie, &amp; Chaſtitie.</p>
                        <p>Two after receauing; Thankeſgiuing, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life.</p>
                        <p>One may likewiſe meditate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the B. Sacrament, and vpon the Prayer, <hi>Deus qui nobis ſub Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento mirabili &amp;c.</hi> And vpon ſome ſentence of the ſame, as, <hi>Caro mea verè eſt cibus. Panem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum manducauit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo:</hi> my fleſh is meare
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:12413:97"/> indeede. Man hath ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the bread of Angels, and the like.</p>
                        <p>One may take for matter to meditate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 6. Chapter of Saint Iohn. The 4. booke of Gerſon. The Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme. The Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Lucas Pinellus, Lewis of Granado, &amp; Fuluius Androtius, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Treatiſes which they haue made of the holie Communion.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="192" facs="tcp:12413:98"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>Maners to Meditate the Benefites of Almighty God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe may conſider in one Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all the benefits of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God; the which, becauſe they are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, hee muſt make two ſeuerall Rolles.</p>
                     <p>One, of the General, and moſt principall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitesl theſe are: Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Conſeruation, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:12413:98"/> Faith, or to be a Chriſtian, Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Communion, and Vocation to his holie ſeruice.</p>
                     <p>Another of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Benefits, as, To be borne of a good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and a good mother. To haue a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, and his health. To haue bene deliuered from ſome ſickneſſe, or danger. Euerie one may repeate his owne, &amp; hee muſt know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by hart, and pauſe a little vpon euerie Benefite.</p>
                     <pb n="194" facs="tcp:12413:99"/>
                     <p>2. One may diuide the benefites of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God into ſundrie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions. 1. The Benefits of Nature, of Grace, and Acquired.</p>
                     <p>2. Of the Soule, of the Bodie, and Exterior<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. Paſt, preſent, and to come. 4. Common to all men, to many, to fewe, to mee onely: and vpon each ranke or kinde of benefites, one may make, one, or more Meditations.</p>
                     <p>3. One may take the ſeuen Benefites aforſaid,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:12413:99"/> and pauſe vpon them ſo long, as he may, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie thinges. Vpon one Benefite, one may make all theſe conſiderations.</p>
                     <p>Who hath done me this Benefite? God.</p>
                     <p>What hath mooued him to doe it? his only Bounty.</p>
                     <p>Wherefore he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it me? For his owne honour, and for my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                     <p>How great is this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite?</p>
                     <p>How much I am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliged
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:12413:100"/> vnto him for the ſame?</p>
                     <p>How vngratefull I haue bene vnto him, &amp; how euillie I haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued my ſelfe of this Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite?</p>
                     <p>What I ought to doe for the time to come.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Maners of Meditating the life of our Ladie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONe may Meditat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the life of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, euen as the life of
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:12413:100"/> our Lord, beginning from her Conception, vntill her Aſſumption, as Coſterus hath done in his booke of the fifty Meditations, vpon the life of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>2. To meditate the principall myſteries of her life, which are thoſe that holie Church doth ſolemniſe: to wit, her Conception, Natiuitie, Annunciation, Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Purification, and Aſſumption.</p>
                     <p>3. To conſider the <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> after the ſelfe
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:12413:101"/> ſame maner, as the <hi>Pater noster.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4. Her vertues; See Arrias, of the Imitation of our Ladie.</p>
                     <p>5. Her Priuiledges.</p>
                     <p>6. Some Hymne of our Ladie, or ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of holy Scripture, appertaining vnto her.</p>
                     <p>7. One may alſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate the figures and prophecies of our B. Ladie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="199" facs="tcp:12413:101"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>The manner of Meditating the Feastes of the Saints.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Taken out of S. Bernard vpon the Sermon of the Vigill of S. Peter and S. Paul.</head>
                        <p>ONe muſt conſider three thinges; The aſiſtance of the Saint. His example. And our confuſion.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>His Helpe.</head>
                        <p>In what place he now
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:12413:102"/> findeth him ſelfe.</p>
                        <p>With what glorie he is crowned.</p>
                        <p>That by his merits and prayers, he can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt me.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>His examples.</head>
                        <p>How he is arriued to this glorie.</p>
                        <p>By what workes, paines, and vertues.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Our confuſion.</head>
                        <p>What doe I? I will come where he is, and will not doe what he hath done.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="201" facs="tcp:12413:102"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>The maner of meditating the vertues.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt one muſt haue a Rolle of vertues: whereof theſe are the principall. Faith, Hope, Loue of God, Feare of God, Prudence, Iuſtice, Humilitie, Patience, Obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Meekeneſſe, Chaſtitie, Pouertie, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, Mercie, Tacitur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Simplicitie, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, Magnanimitie, Perſeuerance.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="202" facs="tcp:12413:103"/>1. One may meditate manye vertues in one Meditation, as the three Theologicall, the foure Cardinall, or the three Euangelicall Counſels, Pouertie, Chaſtitie, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: making of each vertue, one point of Meditation.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. One may take the ſeauen greater or more eminent vertues, as the three Theological, and the foure Cardinall. Or thoſe which are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the ſeuen capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:12413:103"/> vices, and to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate then within one weeke, euery day one.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. One may meditate al the aforeſaid vertues, euerie day one, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo if one will; as the Contempt of the world, the Contempt of him ſelfe, Zeale of ſoules, Deuotion, Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence towardes the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice, Concorde, Veritie, Fidelitie, Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie, Prudence, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or knowledging of Benefites, and Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="204" facs="tcp:12413:104"/>4. One may take one only vertue, and ſtay him ſelfe thereon, ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as hee can, conſidering diuers thinges vpon the ſame, as;</p>
                     <p>What ſuch a vertue is (for example of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:) wherin it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth: and what it meaneth to be humble.</p>
                     <p>How faire, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, profitable, and neceſſarie this vertue is, conſideringe in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the profite that it bringeth.</p>
                     <p>How much it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:12413:104"/> almightie God, and maketh a man accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto him.</p>
                     <p>What example and doctrine our Lord hath giuen vs of ſuch a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
                     <p>How deteſtable, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageable, and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the contrarie vice is vnto Almightie God.</p>
                     <p>How farre off I haue hitherto bene from this vertue, and what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e cauſe thereof hath bene.</p>
                     <p>What I ought to doe for the time to come,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:12413:105"/> conſidering the meanes to acquire the ſame, and the impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to keep me from them.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The fifth meanes is, to Meditate ſome ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in the perſon of our B. Bauiour, conſidering three points.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. What example the Sonne of Almightie God hath giuen vs of this vertue (for example of humilitie.)</p>
                     <p n="2">2. What he hath ſaid and taught touchinge ſuch a vertue, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring him ſelfe of ſome
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:12413:105"/> one ſentence.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Wherefore he hath done and ſaid all this? Aſſuredly for me.</p>
                     <p>In this manner one may meditate in one weeke, ſeuen principall vertues of our Lord and and Sauiour; as, Sunday Charitie. Munday. Munday, Humilitie. Tueſday, Patience. Wenſday, Obedience. Thurſday Meekenes. Friday, Pouertie. Saterday, Chaſtitie.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To meditate the Beatitudes, which are
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:12413:106"/> eight moſt goodlie ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, conſidering three thinges vpon each Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The ſentence it ſelfe, which hath two points, to wit, the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; the recompence.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. How much this vertue hath ſhined in our B. Sauiour.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. How far I am from this vertue, and what profite it would bringe mee, if I were owner thereof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="209" facs="tcp:12413:106"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>The manner how to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, vpon the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BY the conſideration of the creatures, one commeth vnto a great knowledge and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Creator: for there is not any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how little ſoeuer hee be, which ſhewes not the power, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and great boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of him that made
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:12413:107"/> him. Wherfore, who ſo deſireth well and truly to profite in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, let him giue him ſelfe to the reading of this great and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly booke of the world, which is alwaies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en vnto all; &amp; that therein he make manye good and frequent meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the which may be done in two ſortes or maners, to wit;</p>
                     <p>Either meditating them altogether, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all this whole world, in one Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:12413:107"/> or in particular, making one Meditation vpon each creature, as, the heauen, the earth, and obſeruing alwayes therein, the power, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and bountie of almightie God.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore that he accuſtome him ſelfe howerly, or at euery oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, ſeeing any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a beaſt, a flower, &amp;c. to eleuate his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, &amp; to conſider who hath made it, &amp; foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſhall finde the three aforeſaid vertues
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:12413:108"/> and diuine perfections.</p>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Vpon the Creatures in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. The Creatures of the world, euidently ſhewe the greatnes of God, Creator thereof.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The multitude and varietie of the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges created, the infinite perfections which are in God.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. The good diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and Order of the worlde, the wiſedome of God.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. The profite which the creatures doe bring
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:12413:108"/> vnto vs, the Bounty of God.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. The Beautie of the worlde, the beautie of God.</p>
                        <p n="6">6. The roundnes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (which <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>hath neither beginning nor ending) the eternitie of God.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. The vnitie of the worlde, demonſtrateth that God is onely one.</p>
                        <p n="8">8. The aboundance of good thinges, which we receaue of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſheweth the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallitie of God.</p>
                        <p n="9">9. The ſtabilitie and
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:12413:109"/> Conſtancy of the world (continuing alwaies the ſame) ſheweth that God is immutable, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="part">
                        <head>Vpon each Creature in particular.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. To conſider its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which is God.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. The ende wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch a creature hath bene made, to wit, for the honor of God, and ſeruice of man.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Whereof, &amp; how it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h bene made.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. The qualities, and effectes of the ſame crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="215" facs="tcp:12413:109"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>The maner how to meditate the perfections of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt one muſt haue a Rolle; theſe are: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Eſſence, Power, Wiſedome, Bountie, Loue, Mercie, Iuſtice, Prouidence, Liberallity, Patience, and Meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p>Then one muſt know and conſider the workes and effects which he
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:12413:110"/> hath ſhewed, of ſuch and ſuch a vertue; The examples &amp; ſentences of holie Scripture will greatly ſerue thereto. As, to know his diuine Eſſence, to conſider the ſentence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie, cap. 2. ſaying, <hi>I doe fill both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth.</hi> And Acts 3. <hi>In him we liue, mooue, and haue our being.</hi> For the Power of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God. <hi>He ſpake and they were made: he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and they were created.</hi> Pſalm. 32. And
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:12413:110"/> ſo of others. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this meditation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth eſpeciallye to thoſe that are moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and moſt practiſed, as well in Holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as in ſpirituall matters: and therefore may be called, the moſt excellent of all Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>The manner how to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Pater noster, &amp; the holie Scripture.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is an excellent good manner, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:12413:111"/> profitable, to meditate vpon the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Holie Scripture, which are the wordes of Almightie God, and marueilouſly repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with diuine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                     <p>The maner how to meditate them, is, to take the firſt worde of a ſentence (as if it were this;) <hi>So God loued the World, that hee gaue his only begetten Sonne.</hi> Ioh. 3. The firſt word wherof is <hi>So,</hi> &amp; to ſtaye him ſelfe, and to pauſe
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:12413:111"/> vpon the conſideration thereof, ſo long as our ſoule can finde diuerſity of conceits and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, guſt, and vtilitie therein: &amp; then to paſſe to the next word after, and to doe the like.</p>
                     <p>After this maner, one may meditate the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects and Hymnes of holy Church, &amp; aboue all, our Lordes Prayer, the which for that it was compoſed imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly by God himſelfe, conteineth in it verie wounderfull myſteries,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:12413:112"/> and ought to be often Meditated and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for the great fruits which ſuch Meditation bringeth.</p>
                     <p>After this diuine Prayer, to Meditate the <hi>Aue Maria, Salue Regina, Anima Christi, Veni Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Veni ſancte Spiritus, Te Deum laudamus &amp;c.</hi> And Prieſts the Holie Canon of the Maſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of Examen of Conſcience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe examen of Conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:12413:112"/> principallie in knowinge our faultes (which is an act of the vnderſtanding) one may very well place it, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſpecies of Meditation.</p>
                     <p>Now, there are two ſortes of examen of Conſcience; the one is called Generall, when one examineth and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth foorth al the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by Thoughtes, Words, Works, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to the end to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend himſelfe of al; and
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:12413:113"/> ordinarily is made in the Euening, &amp; containeth ſixe points.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To render thankes to Almightie God for his Benefites.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To aske him grace to know our ſinnes, and to amende them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To aske an account of our owne ſoule, of the ſinnes committed that preſent day: conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all the houres of the day from the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wherein we haue failed, by Thoughtes, Wordes Workes, and
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:12413:113"/> Omiſſion.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To demaund par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for that wherein wee haue offended.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To purpoſe firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to amende vs, by the helpe and grace of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God: and to ſay at the ending, the <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The other, is called Particular, and is, when one examineth one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imperfection, wherof one deſireth to correct him ſelfe; the practiſe is this.</p>
                     <pb n="224" facs="tcp:12413:114"/>
                     <p>In the morning being riſen, one muſt inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently make a ſtedfaſt purpoſe, to keepe him ſelfe diligently in that day, from ſuch a fault and imperfection, with the helpe and aſſiſtance of Almighty God.</p>
                     <p>After dinner to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him ſelfe vpon the fame, ſequeſtringe him ſelfe a parte, and doing three particular things.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To demand an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compte of his owne ſoule, conſideringe all the houres fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:12413:114"/> how ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee hath fallen into the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To make ſo many markes, or ſtreekes with his penne.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To purpoſe a new, to countergard him ſelfe for the reſt of that day.</p>
                     <p>After ſupper, to doe the very ſame; And to ſee from day to day, and from one weeke to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, the profite and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment which one hath made; alwaies cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the aſſiſtance of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, to inable him to amend himſelfe,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:12413:115"/> and excitinge him ſelfe, to greater amendment.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>That Which hee muſt doe before Prayer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FOr final accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the forme or manner of Prayer, and of all that which hath bene hitherto ſaid, we drawinge and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachinge nowe to an ende, wee will ſhewe the practiſe, diuiding the ſame into three partes,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:12413:115"/> to the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to obſerue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; that one may the better beare it in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And let euery one perſwade him ſelfe, that by how much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee ſhall obſerue theſe inſtructions and documents, ordinarily, by ſo much better will prayer ſucceede with him; as contrariwiſe, if he vſe not the diligence well to obſerue them, ſo much leſſe progreſſe will he make.</p>
                     <p>The thing then which is moſt neceſſary before
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:12413:116"/> Prayer, is, to make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent preparation, a doctrine and precept gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by almightie God himſelfe; and in the auncient Teſtament al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Wiſeman. (Eccleſ. 8.) ſaying, to whomſoeuer will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelfe before his diuine Maieſty, to ſpeak vnto him; <hi>Before Prayer prepare thy hart, and be not as one that tempteth God.</hi> As if he ſaid; It is too much preſumption, it is a haynous offence, to come before my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:12413:116"/> without firſt put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy ſelfe in order. And by his Sonne in the new (Mat. 6. Where hee ſaieth.) <hi>When thou wilt pray, enter into thy chamber,</hi> that is to ſay, enter within thy ſelfe, prepare thee wel &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>This diligence and preparation, conſiſteth in the doing of ſundrie things.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. One muſt exactly know the hiſtorie, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, or ſubiect which wee meane to meditate, and the circumſtances
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:12413:117"/> of the ſame, as the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, the perſons, &amp; other particularities; for the knowledge of the fact, is the ground of the Meditation: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, one muſt either read the Text, or a litle refreſh the memorie thereof.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. One muſt deuide the aforeſaid ſubiect or matter of meditation, into ſundrie parcells or parts, which we call points or conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the ende, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:12413:117"/> And then alſo, one muſt prepare the preludiums and collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, conforme to the ſubiect of the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: whereof ſhall be ſpoken, in the enſuing Article.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is not ſo good in meditatinge, to take ſome meditation made by another all at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, as of S. Bonauenture, Granado, or others: for better it is, that the ſoule of her ſelfe doe finde her owne paſture.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. One muſt not be
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:12413:118"/> weary, either in bodie or minde, when one goeth to prayer, as to haue read or written o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch: but for ſome time before, to leaue al, to finde him ſelfe freſh and wel, diſpoſed, at the time of Prayer.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. About one quarter before the houre (if the prayer be made by day, and the Euening before he goe to bed, for that of the morning) one muſt diligentlie fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and learne by hart, the points of the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:12413:118"/> &amp; the reſt which one hath prepared for this purpoſe, yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and if neede ſo require (at the time of prayer, to hould the paper or booke in his hande, the better to remember and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate one thinge after another.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Being layde in his bed, he muſt briefelie reduce them to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie; and ariſing in the morning, giue and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the firſt of his thoughts vnto almighty God, &amp; then make him
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:12413:119"/> ſelfe readie, thanking him, and praying vnto him, both with heart &amp; mouth, and thinking v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſubiect of the Meditation that hee meaneth to make, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite in him ſelfe a fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire to doe it well.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. About a quarter of an houre before, one muſt doe that which onr Sauiour ſaith (in S. Mat. cap. 6.) <hi>Enter into thy chamber &amp;c.</hi> Enter into thy ſelfe, and cloſe the gate againſt al other
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:12413:119"/> affaires and cogitations, conſideringe, whether one goeth, and where about: and houlding him ſelfe ſo recollec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to attende and expect the houre of Prayer.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. It is alſo good to goe to prayer, with a good appetite, that is to ſay, with inclination &amp; deſire to pray. And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thoſe who want an appetite, labour to get one, either by doing ſome exerciſe, or by ſawces, and the like,
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:12413:120"/> which procure an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite: euen ſo muſt one ſeeke for deuotion (not hauing the ſame) either by reading, or by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of conſcience, or lookinge fixedly vpon ſome ſweete and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout Picture, or doing ſome Penance, as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, or other morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; Moreouer, the more to ſtirre vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he muſt, going to Prayer, thinke that he goes to a mine of gould or ſiluer, from whence he may bring, moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:12413:120"/> treaſure.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Then, hauing heard the clockes, or the time being arriued, thou ſhalt take holie water, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to thine ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to driue awaie the Deuill. Next, thou ſhalt goe faire and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie towardes the place where thou oughteſt to pray; and ſtanding one or two ſteppes off, before thou falleſt on thy knees, pauſe a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and raiſe vpp thy ſpirit on high, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe on the one ſide,
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:12413:121"/> the greatnes of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, &amp; his preſence, howe hee looketh vpon thee: on the otherſide, thy ſmalnes, and thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and that he atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee, to giue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge and curteous au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. After this, thou ſhalt make him an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deuout reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, ſetting thy knees vpon the ground, ſaying wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h heart and mouth, ſometimes the wordes of the Patriarch Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, I <hi>will ſpeake to my</hi>
                        <pb n="239" facs="tcp:12413:121"/> 
                        <hi>Lord,</hi> I <hi>that am but duſt and others:</hi> ſometimes thoſe of S. Francis, <hi>Lord who art thou, &amp; who am I?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="11">11. Going to prayer, it will greatly helpe thee (as in all other thinges) to recommend thy ſelfe to thy Angell gardian, and to beſeech him that he wil accompany thee, and bringe thee before thy Lord, and to aſſiſt thee at that inſtant, and that he would put back &amp; hinder all diſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and both pray for thee, and likewiſe preſent thy
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:12413:122"/> prayers to Almightie God.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. Thou muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe inſtructions, allwaies notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding without ſcruple or anxietie, neuer to forget anie thing: for ſometimes it chanceth (eſpeciallie to the moſt perfect and moſt habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated) that without ſo much preparation, one findeth him ſelfe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and one preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ereth into the wine celler of our B. Lord:
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:12413:122"/> it ſufficeth that we all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doe on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, our endeuour &amp; diligence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>That which is to be done, during Prayer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>DVring the houre, or time of Prayer, there are foure things to be performed, to wit; The Preparatorie Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the PreIudiums, the Points, and the Colloquies. Order is
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:12413:123"/> good in euery thing, &amp; the holye Scripture (Deuteronomie 31.) that the thinges of God are wel diſpoſed. Now to vnderſtand thoſe wordes, and maner of ſpeaking.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Preparatorie</hi> prayer is called, a briefe praier, which is made in the minde at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of prayer and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, offering vpp to God, all our faculties and operations, to his honour and glorie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding his aſſiſtance
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:12413:123"/> to make our prayer, of whom all our ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.) And one may adde thereto the vocall Prayer, <hi>Actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes nostras. &amp;c.</hi> or ſome other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Preludium,</hi> is as a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble which aideth the ſoule &amp; vnderſtanding, to enter the more eaſily into Meditation. And ordinarily one maketh two Preludiums, after the Preparatorie Prayer. Now, to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d how one muſt make theſe Prea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, note that the
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:12413:124"/> matter of Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be of two ſortes, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, as the Natiuitie of our Lorde; or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, as Sinne.</p>
                     <p>The firſt Preludium, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the matter, is Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and viſible, is, to imagine the perſons, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as if we ſawe them before our eyes. As for example, if we will meditate the Natiuitie of our Lord, the firſt Preludium ſhal be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent before our eyes the Stable, the Manger, the little Infant, our
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:12413:124"/> Ladie, and S. Ioſeph. And euen as the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters repreſent them to vs in their Pictures: the ſame are we to doe in our imagination; proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded without too exceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue inforcement, for they which haue not a good imagination, ſhould breake their heades in vaine; and others make great pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ite thereof.</p>
                     <p>When the matter is Spirituall, one muſt vſe ſome other like repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; as for example, to imagine to ſee our
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:12413:125"/> ſoule encloſed within this bodie, as within a priſon; or man baniſhed into this vale of teares, amongſt the brute and ſauage beaſtes; or to ſee him ſelf enuironed with diuels; or to be amidſt the Angels; or to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to heare a voice from heauen; or from the mouth of our Lord, or other Prophet or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpeaking or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncinge the wordes which one will Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Prelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:12413:125"/> is, to craue of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, the grace which one deſireth to drawe from ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as ſorrow for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, loue of God, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him ſelfe, &amp;c. conforme to the ſubiect of the Meditation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Colloquie</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> (taking the word praier, properlie) is al one, that is to ſay, to ſpeake with God, as hath before bene explicated &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. After then that one hath contemplated &amp; conſidered; one muſt
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:12413:126"/> next pray, that is to ſay, ſpeake with almightie God, thanking him, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon of him, or the like. Briefly, doing that which hath bene ſaid in its place. Now we will adioyne three things, to wit; how one muſt make theſe Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies; how many, and when.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. As touching the firſt (beſides that which hath bene ſaid in his place touching the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner howe to Thanke, Aske, &amp; Offer, in which
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:12413:126"/> three doe ordinarilie conſiſt the Colloquie) Note firſt that all this ought to be done men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallie and in ſpirit; albeit after the ſame, one may adioyne ſome Vocall prayer, ſuch as one will, and according to the ſubiect of the Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ordinarilie, at the ende of the prayer, one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght to recite that diuine prayer, by the which one craueth of almightie God, all that which may be dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and deſired, to wit, our
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:12413:127"/> Lordes Prayer; But it muſt be ſaid, ſoftlie or leaſurelie, worde by worde.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To make this Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie well, one thinge there is which doeth greatly ayde, which is, to ſpeake vnto Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, one while, as a little infant ſpeaketh to his father, another while as the ſeruant ſpeaketh to his maiſter, the vaſſall to his king: Now as the ſpouſe ſpeaketh to hir betrothed: and ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as a poore begger
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:12413:127"/> to the rich; as a guiltie perſon to his Iudge, as one ſicke to his Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian: and imagining him ſelf like to the Prodigall childe, lame, leprous, a traitour, rebell, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is alſo good to make ſome mentall dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, which is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce our Lord, or God the Father ſo ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the ſoule, and ſaying vnto him, ſuch or ſuch like thinges: and the ſoule anſwering him. Or contrariwiſe, the ſoule ſpeakinge, and
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:12413:128"/> God anſwering her.</p>
                     <p>As touchinge the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, one may make one Colloquie onely, as to God the Father, or to our Lord Ieſus: and one may likewiſe make ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie if one will.</p>
                     <p>Take an example of three Colloquies, Firſt, to addreſſe vs to the bleſſed Virgin, beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching her to obtaine for vs the thing which we deſire, or which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for vs: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing prayed Mentally, to make another Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:12413:128"/> with our Lord, as he is man, and our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour, beſeeching him mentally, to obtaine for vs the ſame grace, and immediatly to recite ſome praier which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to him, as, <hi>Anima Christi;</hi> or ſome other. The third Colloquie, with God the Father, that it would pleaſe his Maieſtie, by the Merits and interceſſion of the Mother and the Sonne, to graunt vs that which we demaund; and at the ende, to recite the
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:12413:129"/> 
                        <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As touching the third, albeit the proper place and time of the Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, be at the ende of an howre, and neuer to omit to departe from Prayer, without making ſome kind of Colloquy; neuertheles one may alſo make them in the middeſt, and at euerie point and conſideration, when the ſoule doeth finde her ſelfe mooued and ſtirred vp to ſay or ſpeake ſomethinge. Or the better, to continue
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:12413:129"/> attention, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard himſelfe from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theſe little Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies. I ſay little, becauſe if the Colloquie at the beginninge or midſt of the meditation ſhould be long, it would hinder the Meditation: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that which comes from the Holie Ghoſt, cannot be but good; whence we ſee, that there are certaine perſons, who ſpend the time of Prayer and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, by manner of Colloquie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="256" facs="tcp:12413:130"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>That which is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vpon the points of Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HAuinge ſhewed howe manie thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges there are to be done in the time and houre of prayer or meditation; next we will note that which is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon each point, wherin many doe finde them ſelues troubled, not knowinge what to thinke or meditate. To
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:12413:130"/> helpe therefore all the world, and to giue vnto all ſufficient matter and meanes to entertaine them ſelues in medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to profite ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, we will ſet before them ſundry Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which one may make vpon all thinges whatſoeuer they be.</p>
                     <p>Note then, that the matter which one medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth is, either Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or Spirituall. If the ſubiect be Corporall (as are all the miſteries of our Lord) one muſt
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:12413:131"/> vpon each point conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe circumſtances, to wit, 1. The perſons who are found in this miſterie, as our Lord, our Ladie, the Angell Gabriell, the Apoſtles, &amp;c. And their qualities, vertues, excellence, and office, 2. The wordes which each of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: and when there are no wordes written, to thinke what probably they might ſay in ſuch a caſe. 3. That which eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one doth. 4. The
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:12413:131"/> ende and cauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame was done. 5. The effects and vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which haue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thereof. 6. One may alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, the though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; affections, which thoſe perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had in that inſtant.</p>
                     <p>If the matter be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, there are diuers things to be conſidered. 1. What ſuch a thing or matter is. 2. What his firſt beginning, and cauſe efficient is. 3. Wherfore, and to what ende, it hath bene done. 4. The
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:12413:132"/> vtilities or detriments, that it doeth produce. 5. What our Lord hath done or ſaid of ſuch a thinge. 6. How I haue comported my ſelfe in times paſt, concerninge the ſame. 7. What I ought to doe for the time to come. 8. It is verie good to conſider the name, or the diuers names of ſuch a thing. 9. And ſome ſentence of Holie Scripture v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſame ſubiect. Behould then, if there be aboundant matter
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:12413:132"/> to ſtay ones ſelfe in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation or not. But one muſt knowe theſe points by heart, a litle alſo accuſtome himſelfe, or hould this booke, or this paper in his hande.</p>
                     <p>And note, that it is not neceſſarie euery daie to make theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, but onely ſome: nor yet exactly to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame order, as, to conſider alwayes, all the perſons in the firſt place, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the wordes, and ſo
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:12413:133"/> foorth, but accordinge as the ſoule ſhall faſten her ſelfe, rather to one thing, then to another.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXXII. <hi>Of the Compoſition of the Bodie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere is yet another thing to be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to be explicated, which is, the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodie; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſundrie thinges are to be noted.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That it imports
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:12413:133"/> not how one place, or ſettle him ſelfe in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, or praying, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided that the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Prayer it ſelfe ſucceede wel, be it knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or ſtanding, or ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or lying, orleaning, or lying proſtrate on the ground, or houldinge the armes in forme of a Croſſe. Walking, is not proper to Meditate, but rather to prepare one before, and to examine after prayer.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſoeuer it be, one
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:12413:134"/> muſt obſerue great reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect and reuerence, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies remembring, that one is in the ſight and preſence of Almightie God, and to be verie warie, not to doe the leaſt indecent thing that may be. And albeit that greater reuerence is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the acts of the Will, then in the actes of the Vnderſtandinge, that is to ſaie, that one muſt comporte himſelfe more reuerentlie and more humblie, when one prayeth, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:12413:134"/> Colloquies, then when one conſidereth only, notwithſtandinge in meditating one muſt not forget the reuerence due to his maieſtie; and therefore albeit one ſit, he muſt be bare-headed, if that his health permit the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That ordinarilie one muſt begin vpon his knees, or proſtrate; and after that one hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in ſuch faſhion, he muſt not ſtirre, but hould him ſelfe ſo, ſo
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:12413:135"/> long as the bodie doeth feele no paine, and that his prayer ſucceedeth well. Then when it ſhal be neede, to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date him ſelfe faire and ſoftly in ſome other maner.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. As touching the eies, for the moſt part, he muſt hould them ſhut, to praye and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate well. One may alſo ſometimes open them, but fixed on ſome certaine place, without moouing them this way and that way.</p>
                     <pb n="267" facs="tcp:12413:135"/>
                     <p>All this being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed, the practiſe is this. That being placed vpon his knees, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate vpon the ground, after he hath bleſt him with the ſigne of the Croſſe, immediatly he muſt make the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie prayer with great diffidence in him ſelfe, and confidence in God.</p>
                     <p>After that the Prelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diums; Which done, he muſt take the firſt point of the Meditation, and conſideringe the ſame, ſtay him ſelfe, or pauſe
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:12413:136"/> ſo long time thereon, as the ſoule doth finde to thincke and to profite theron; &amp; then to paſſe to the other, and to do the ſame. At the ende of the houre, or after one hath meditated e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to make the Colloquie, or Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, and makinge an ende, to recite deuoutly the <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And becauſe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt difficultie in this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faire lieth in the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſideration of the points, to the end
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:12413:136"/> that euery one be well inſtructed, we will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioine ſome other aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, that muſt be vſed in this behalfe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Other aduertiſements tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Meditation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. THe firſt is, that if it chance (as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metimes it doeth) that in meditatinge the firſt point, or the ſecond, the meditation ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth well, and that the
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:12413:137"/> ſoule findeth therein manie thinges to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and profite her ſelfe, he muſt ſtaie him there, not caring to paſſe to the other point, albeit the whole houre ſhould be ſpent therin: only hee muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to make the Colloquy at the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The ſecond, that hee muſt not content himſelfe with the onely conſideration, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thinges, but to paſſe further, and to mooue the will, and to doe as the Prophet ſaith:
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:12413:137"/> 
                        <hi>pſ. 8. In my Meditation, fire is kindled.</hi> Now the moſt ordinary affections which one ought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite in time of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, are, Loue, Feare, Sorrow, Ioye, Deſire, Hope, Admiration, and Confuſion of him ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>It is meete then, that the meditation be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>drie, and onely pure ſpeculation, but affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and full of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour taſte. Moreouer, of euerie point which one conſidereth, one muſt endeuour to draw
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:12413:138"/> ſome fruite, making re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection vpon him ſelfe, and reſoluingto execute that which the Holie Ghoſt hath taught vs in our Prayer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The third, that the ſentences of the holy Scriptures, do greatly helpe to meditate well: and for this reſpect it is good, to find out &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſome one vpon the ſame ſubiecte, whereon hee will Meditate; As to Meditate vpon the knowledge of himſelfe, &amp; of the miſeries of ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="273" facs="tcp:12413:138"/> in this world, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider this ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Iob. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cap. 14, A man borne of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp;c.</hi> And making a meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the loue of God towards man, to take this ſentence of our Lord. (Ioh. 3.) <hi>So God loued the world. &amp;c.</hi> and ſo of other matters.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The fourth, that ſimilitudes alſo do mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellouſlie ayde to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate well, for the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of this world, doe leade vs to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of inuiſible and ſpirituall thinges; as for
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:12413:139"/> example: wilt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and comprehend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſomething of the glorie of heauen? Take ſome ſimilitudes of Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quets, Marriages, Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and Pleaſures of this preſent life. In like maner, to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the paines of hell, propoſe vnto thy ſelfe the moſt grieuous tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the greateſt euils of this world: and the very ſame thou muſt doe in other matters.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Application of the Senſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. The fifth is, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:12413:139"/> the application of the Senſes, which is a thing that doth ayde &amp; further meditation, and are placed onely in thoſe Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whoſe matter is Corporal. To apply the Sences in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating, is as much to ſay, as to imagine to ſee, heare, ſmell, taſte, and touch ſpirituallie and by deuotion, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſons contained in the meditation, their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſteppes, and all things elſe appertaining vnto them: but this is
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:12413:140"/> to be done with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie and reuerence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> And this application o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Senſes, is made or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily a part, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; in another houre or euen then alſo, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> after meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after &amp; the diſcourſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is ended.</p>
                     <p>There is another for of application of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Senſes, or rather medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation vpon the Senſes which is, to conſider for example, that which our Lord ſufferedin e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:12413:140"/> of his Senſes, or the ioy, and contentment that our Ladie receaued of our Lord, by her Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, beholding him, hearing him ſpeakinge to him, touching him &amp;c. Alſo to conſider the ioyes, that the bleſſedſhal haue and the paines which the damned ſhall ſuffer in the fiue Senſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXXIV. <hi>Remedies against di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stractions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe ſixt is, touching the diſtractions
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:12413:141"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="277" facs="tcp:12413:141"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="278" facs="tcp:12413:142"/> which chance in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and meditating, and like vnto dead flyes, ſpil the ſweetneſſe of the oyntment. (Eccleſ. 10.) one muſt therfore know the remedies. And firſt, to make a diligent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, as hath bene ſaide, to aske ayde of almightie God, and our Angell Gardian for this effect. 2. Becauſe medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is more ſubiect to diſtraction then pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; one remedie is, not to continue ouer long the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:12413:142"/> is the act of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but to each conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to adde ſome prayer, or a litle Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquie.</p>
                     <p>There are other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to driue awaie the diſtraction, which is all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie entred. Firſt one muſt be diligent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to take notice of it, and ſpeedely to reiect it. 2. Humblie to craue pardon of almightie God, to haue turned our backe towardes him. 3. If the diſtraction doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, or wil not awaie,
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:12413:143"/> one muſt not impatient or trouble him ſelfe, ſith comming againſt our will, it is no ſinne, but matter of merit. 4. To humble and confound him ſelfe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering his pouertie &amp; feebleneſſe, not able to doe any good thing of himſelfe, and to eſteeme himſelfe vnworthie to ſpeake vnto God, and to ſtand in his diuine preſence. 5. To recommende him ſelfe to our B. Ladie, to his good Angell, and other Patrons. 6. To
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:12413:143"/> make this vocall Prayer deuoutlie, worde by worde, and to content himſelfe therewith, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he who hauing bread made of wheate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> himſelfe with bread of Rie or Barley. 7. Sometimes not to looſe too much time in this combat of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunat cogitations, one may take ſome good ſpiritual booke, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gerſon &amp; make mixt prayer, and meditation together, reading one period or ſentence, and
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:12413:144"/> conſidering it a litle, &amp; then to make ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall prayer, or Vocal, or the one or other, and ſo to paſſe from period to period. 8. For al diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, difficultie, &amp; paine which may preſent it ſelfe, he muſt neuer for all this abandon prayer, nor ſhorten the time which he hath accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or otherwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to employ therin, which the diuell doth eſpeciallie pretende and labour to perſwade: but in ſuch caſe, he
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:12413:144"/> muſt rather a little paſſe beyond the howre, to the end to vanquiſhe him ſelfe, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Doing this, that which the wiſe man promiſeth wil come to paſſe (Eccleſ. 7.) to wit. That the end of Prayer, ſhall be better then the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that is to ſay, that one ſhall not depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence without conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or at the leaſt, one ſhall merit verye much, mortifying him ſelfe for the loue of God.</p>
                     <pb n="284" facs="tcp:12413:145"/>
                     <p>The ſeauenth, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to Repetition, that is to ſay, that it is expedient, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times neceſſarie, once, twice, and thrice, to make againe the ſame meditation: the which is done for two reaſons; Either for that the firſt time one hath found therin exceeding ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and profite, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing the ſame, he ſhal both taſte and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite more; Or, for that the firſt time he could not enter therein, and
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:12413:145"/> returning thereto, it wil come to paſſe, that at the ſeconde, third, or fourth time, the gate ſhal be ſet open vnto vs, according to that which our Lord teacheth in S. Mark. cap. 7. ſaying: <hi>Knocke and it shal be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto you.</hi> Adde, that by theſe Repetitions, the like myſteries are better imprinted in our ſoule, and alſo the vnderſtanding doeth habituate and make it ſelfe more prompt to meditate.</p>
                     <pb n="286" facs="tcp:12413:146"/>
                     <p>Laſtly, one may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, in three manners: either all the meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or ſome one point ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whereof one could not taſt before: or to Repeate two or three Meditations together, pauſing, eſpecially vpon thoſe points wherein at the firſt one hath found leaſt taſt or reliſh, or which one could not meditate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="287" facs="tcp:12413:146"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XXXV. <hi>What one muſt doe when he is diſguſted, and in ſpiritual aridity or dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe eight is, howe one ought to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne him ſelfe, and what he ought to doe, in the time of ariditie, or drineſſe. Where it is to be noted, that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life, albeit for the moſt part it be full of ſweetneſſe and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:12413:147"/> of ſpirite, for the vertuous people ſake, who enforce themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues truely to ſerue our Lord, notwithſtanding it is ſometimes ſubiect to deſolation &amp; diſtaſte, ſo that a man hauing loſt this ſenſible deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, doeth finde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe drie, not able to bide at prayer and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. Now, finding him ſelfe in ſuch eſtate, what muſt he doe? 1. He muſt neuer looſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but expect with firme hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:12413:147"/> that God after this ſtorme will ſende faire weather, as Tobie ſaid, cap. 3. <hi>Who after tempeſt; ſendeth faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> 2. To haue pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and to ſay with Iob (cap. 1.) <hi>If wee haue receaued good things from the handes of our Lord, is it not iuſt that we receau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> alſo euill?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3. To humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, lauding almightie God, for at that time wee ſee, and touch with the finger, that wee are nothing woorth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:12413:148"/> the aide of almightie God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Alſo, wee ought to beleeue, that this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not but through our faul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es and offences; for the which God doth preſently puniſh vs, and hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly to aske him par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Beſids this, he muſt likewiſe vſe other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to recouer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion which one hath loſt for the former would not ſuffice.</p>
                     <p>4. The fourth then is, to doe ſome Penan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, or Penances to this ende.</p>
                     <pb n="291" facs="tcp:12413:148"/>
                     <p>5. To examine more diligently his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to take awaie the cauſe of euill.</p>
                     <p>6. To recommend himſelfe more inſtantly vnto our Lord, to our Ladie, to his good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell &amp;c. And he muſt be aduertiſed, that in ſuch time of diſtaſtfulnes, he muſt not omit any good worke which he was accuſtomed or delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before to doe, nor yet to ſeeke himſelfe, nor his proper guſt, but the honor &amp; good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:12413:149"/> of Almightie God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XXXVI. <hi>That which is to be done after Prayer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AFter that Prayer is finiſhed, one muſt make a particular exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vpon the ſame prayer, in this maner. Either ſittinge or wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king faire and ſoftly, to conſider the ſpace of a quarter of an houre, or there about, how thy prayer hath ſucceeded
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:12413:149"/> with thee, well or ill; If thou haſt had good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, render thankes to the diuine bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thy ſelfe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging that this good proceedeth not of thy ſelfe; If thy affaires went ill, humbly aske him pardon.</p>
                     <p>2. Examine &amp; ſearch out the cauſe whence this proceeded, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering from point to point, how, and with what dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, thou haſt performed that which was to be obſerued, and
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:12413:150"/> wherein thou haſt fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: and make a firme purpoſe to be more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and to doe better for the time to come.</p>
                     <p>3. Retaine in memory ſome fruite of the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which almighty God hath communicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, to make thy profite thereof.</p>
                     <p>4. After this, giue a glance of the eye to all the day enſuing, wiſely diſpoſing thine affaires, and purpoſing this and that, as God ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire thee.</p>
                     <pb n="295" facs="tcp:12413:150"/>
                     <p>5. If ſome one after prayer and Meditation, wil commit to writting ſome profitable point, which hee hath recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or felt in medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to the ende to ſerue himſelfe therof for his owne profite, or his neighbours, it is both lawfull, &amp; of great vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; but alwaies proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, let the ſame be done very briefly.</p>
                     <p>6. Sometimes before dinner and ſupper, he muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber himſelfe of the meditation in the
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:12413:151"/> morning, both in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and particularlie of that point which hee had retained, chewing the ſame a litle, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his deuotion, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing that which the Prophet ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ieth. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquiae cogitationis diem festum agent tibi.</hi> Pſal. 75.</p>
                     <p>7. He muſt put in executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, which he made in the morning, taking heed of the occaſions which offer themſelues, much leſſe procuring them: for it is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:12413:151"/> ende and fruit of Prayer.</p>
                     <p>8. In the day time, hee muſt keepe himſelfe cloſely recollected, and as in continuall deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to beware of diſtraction, as much as poſſible may be, not let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Lord goe out of our ſight, and ſaying in euerie place with the Prophet: <hi>I had alwaies our Lord before my ſight. Pſal.</hi> 10.</p>
                     <p>9. Finally, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh all that hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto bene ſaid, and to
<pb n="298" facs="tcp:12413:152"/> profite better in this holy exerciſe of prayer and meditation, the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of Almightie God, ought twice a weeke to make an examen here vpon particularlie, ſith the thing is of ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: that he exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I ſay, how prayer goeth with him, how he aduanceth himſelfe herein, to wit, if there be ſome impediment, and the like: comparing one weeke with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and one moneth with another. And to
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:12413:152"/> make this examen, he muſt ſet down the daies, and the howres, to the ende to remember him, as on Tueſdaie, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdaie; in the morning after Prayer, and in the euening, after ſupper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb n="300" facs="tcp:12413:153"/>
                  <p>Inſtructio haee ad bene orandun, à R. P. Ignatio Balſamo; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita &amp; Anglice red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita vtiliter imprimi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit 12. Aug. 1617. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domaropoli.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. <hi>Redman S. T. Doctor &amp; librorum Cenſor.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Huius iudicio ſubſcripſi Duaci, 37. Auguſti, 1617.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Georgius Coluenerius S. Theol. Doctor &amp; Profeſſor, &amp; libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in Academia Duacena Cenſor.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:153"/>
                  <p>THE FLOWERS OF DEVOTION.</p>
                  <p>Where with euerie pious ſoule, may eaſilie practiſe how to diſcourſe ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, with Ieſus Chriſt his beloued Spouſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Containinge 24. holie Aſpirations, to be recited in eache of the 24. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as well of the night, as of the day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>For IOHN HEIGHAM.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:154"/>
                  <pb n="303" facs="tcp:12413:154"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is vpon Ieſus-Chriſt, your beſt beloued Spouſe (deuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; deare affected ſoule) on whome your hart ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to muſe &amp; meditate. in all your thoughtes, wordes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deedes wills, deſires, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirations, yea euen in all the houres, and moments of your life; It is he, I ſay, Who ought to be imbraced and lodged therin, both night and day, the Idea of your ſoule, the deſire of your hart, and the onlie obiect of all your motions.</p>
                  <p>To the end therfore, neuer so diuide or ſequeſter your
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:12413:155"/> ſelfe from his bleſſed compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, behould here certaine amourous diſcourſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to entertaine you, and where vpon to employ your ſpirit in euerie moment, in manner of Petitions or briefe Meditations, ſo sweete, ſo fruitfull, ſo ſpirituall, yea ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deuout and aggreable to your dearlie beloued Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, as that the ſame is a true and aſſured meanes, and moſt perfect methode, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you perpetuallie in his holie grace, and to dwell with him, and in him, and he likewiſe with you, and within you in all occaſions. Performe then, I beſeeche you, that which is here perſcribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, not for the loue of me (allbeie I inſtantlie require
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:12413:155"/> you) but for the most tender loue which you beare to his diuine maieſtie.</p>
                  <p>You shall begin this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall office at fiue a clock in the Euening, to meditate the firſt Aſpiration &amp; sweete diſcourſe, and ſo from houre to houre you shall continue, vntill the four and twentith houre, which will bring you to finish this exerciſe, at four a clocke, the next day after in the Euening; And then you shall begin againe att your firſt, and ſo shall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue euerie day (Gods grace aſſistinge you) vntill the day and houre, that he shall determine to place you with him ſelfe in perpetuall repoſe.</p>
                  <p>Now, as touching the
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:12413:156"/> houres ordained for reſt, you shall obſerue this eaſie rule. Before you fall a ſleepe, be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethor in your bed, or he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ort you goe to take your reſt, you shall meditat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> four of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Meditations. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if it happen alſo that you awake in the night time, you shall meditate one or two more. If you awaken not all the night, in the morning you shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plish althoſe houres which you haue omitted: and in this ſort you shall alwaies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</p>
                  <p>This holie Exerciſe, you haue meanes to performe in working, talking, walking and in all manner of affaires which you shall doe, for it is nether the bodie, nor yet the tongue which is burthened by
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:12413:156"/> this Exerciſe, but it is the ſpirit &amp; the hare which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and teſtifieth to Ieſus-Christ, the fidelitie and care which it hath to pleaſe him. This alſo may be done, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hindringe you any thinge at all from your other pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ether Mentall, or Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, yea or ſo much as to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould you from attendinge, to any other godlie worke, or laudable Exerciſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer; Practiſe then, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your ſeruant in Chriſt Ieſus. Iohn Heigham.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="meditation">
                  <pb n="308" facs="tcp:12413:157"/>
                  <head>The 1. Meditation, at fiue clock at night.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt meeke Ieſus, the patterne and example of perfect humilitie. In this houre, entring into the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of a frinde, thou vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafedſt to waſh the feete of thy diſciples, in ſigne of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great and ſingular Humility Grant deare Ieſus, that I may obtaine the vertu of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perfect Humilitie, euen t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the abiecting of my ſelfe vnder all mens feete; An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> let it pleaſe thee ſo to waſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my ſinfull ſoule, that I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge thee therein, for eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and euer. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="meditation">
                  <pb n="309" facs="tcp:12413:157"/>
                  <head>The 2. Meditation, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſix a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus. In this houre, euen then whilſt thine enimies conſpired thy death, and ſought to teare thy fleſh in peeces with their teeth, and to drink thy blood for rage and madnes, in the ſame houre, thou vowchſafedſt to inſtitute that moſt diuine Sacrament of thy bodie and blood, for our foode and ſuſtenance. Deare Ieſus, by the vertu of this thy ſweete and ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue, preſerue and keepe me from the ſinne of Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; And neuer ſuffer me to depart this life. till firſt I be fed with thy Bodie and Blood in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="meditation">
                  <pb n="310" facs="tcp:12413:158"/>
                  <head>The 3. Meditation, at ſeauen a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thou wenteſt with thy Diſciples into the garden of Gethſmany, where pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate on the ground, and praying to thy Father, thou felſt into ſuch exceſſiue ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that thou didſt ſweat, a ſweat of blood, for paine and anguiſh. Deare Ieſus, aſiſt me with thy grace, in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations, to haue my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent recourſe vnto thee by holie prayer, and make me in this life, willingly to ſweat with thee, that in the life to come, I may for euer ioifully repoſe with thee. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 4. Meditation, at eight a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:12413:158"/> houre, thou waſt ſould and betrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to thine enimies, by thine owne Diſciple, with the ſigne of a kiſſe, and this for the loue of a litle lucre. Deare Ieſus let no filthie lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, euer cauſe me to ſell or betray thee: or vniuſtlie to wronge or oppreſſe my neighbour. And refuſe not (I beſeeche thee) the kiſſe of him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epenteth to haue offended thee, ſith thou refuſedſt not the kiſſe of him that did vnkindly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 5. Meditation, at nine a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thou waſt bound and faſt tyed by moſt barbarous ſoldiers, and haled by them hither and thither like a very
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:12413:159"/> beaſt, without once opening thy mouth in thine owne defence. Grant me deare Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in vertu of theſe thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bondes, to binde and captiuate, all my ſenſes, both of ſoule and bodie, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto thee. And neuer to hale thee to any beaſtlie ſinne, or voluptuous pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, wherby I may treſpas or offend thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 6. Meditation, at ten a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre thou waſt forſaken of thy Diſciples, and remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt alone in the handes of thine enimies, who led thee away, as their priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and captiue. Deare Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, receiue me, I beſeeche thee, thy fugitiue ſeruant,
<pb n="313" facs="tcp:12413:159"/> who manie times (for feare and other reſpects) haue fled from thee; And keepe me ſafelie vnder thy protection, that mine infernall enimies, doe not carrie me awaye as their condemned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall captiue, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 7. Meditation, ar eleuen a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O good Ieſus, in this houre thou waſt preſented before Annas, who deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded queſtions of thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning both thy doctrine and thy diſciples: and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a violent blow of one of his ſeruants, yet rendredſt vnto that wicked and inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wretch, a moſt milde anſwere, Deare Ieſus, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me to confes thy faith and truth, vpon all occaſions,
<pb n="314" facs="tcp:12413:160"/> when I ſhall be called or vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therunto. Neuer to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh any in the heate of my paſſion: and ſuch as any way ſhall iniurie me, to mollifie their wrathfull hartes with wordes of ſweetnes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 8. Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itation, at twelue a clock at night.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre thou waſt ſent from Annas to Cayphas, where the chiefe of the Prieſts were aſſembled together<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſecking falſe witnes againſt thee to put thee to death: but found not any. Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Ieſus, grant me to accuſe no man falſelie, and being falſtlie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, to ſuppore it patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. To deſpiſe, yea and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie
<pb n="315" facs="tcp:12413:160"/> to deteſt, all lies and falſitie, ſith by lies and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, thou waſt vniuſtlie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged and condemned to die, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 9. Meditation, at one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre, thou was thrice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied of Peeter, who forſwore himſelfe to be thy Diſciple, but thou gratiouſlie looking back vpon him, he preſently went foorth of that wicked companie, and bitterlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed his offence. Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Ieſus, haue mercie on me, who both by wordes and deedes, haue ſo oft denyed my ſelfe to be thy Diſciple. Looke vpon me with the eyes of thy clemencie, for that wherin I haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="316" facs="tcp:12413:161"/> thee: and make mee to flye all wicked companie, ſith the ſame is ſuch an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of falling from thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 10. Meditation, at two a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre, thou waſt ſent from Cayphas, to Pontius Pilat, where the wicked Iewes began a freſh to accuſe thee falſlie, alleadging that thou peruertedſt their people, and forbadſt them to pay tribut to Ceſars Maieſtie; Deare Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, let this thy falſe accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, excuſe me (faultie that I am) before the Maieſtie of thy Father; And make me ſo to giue vnto the world that which is the worldes, that I neuer omitt to giue vnto
<pb n="317" facs="tcp:12413:161"/> God that which is Gods, which is, all honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 11. Meditation, at three a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O good Ieſus, in this houre, thou waſt ſent by Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat to Herod, who of vaine curioſitie, had long time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſee thee: where thou (king of heauen) cloathed in a white coate (the habit of fooles) waſt contemned of him and of his whole court. Deare Ieſus, grant vnto me, a moſt feruent deſire to ſee thee, and to haue thee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie preſent before mine eies; And vtterlie to deteſt all pride of apparell, ſith thou in a coloured and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured coate, waſt mocked
<pb n="318" facs="tcp:12413:162"/> and accounted for a foole. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 12. Meditation, at four a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O good Ieſus, in this houre, thou waſt ſent backe againe by Herod, to Pilat, where thou waſt ſtripped naked, bound to a Pilar, and ſo inhumanlie beaten with roddes and ſcourges, that the blood ran downe on euerie ſide of thy B. bodie. Deare Ieſus, grant me thy grace, nakedlie to diſcouer my ſinnes to my ghoſtlie Father; Willinglie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the rod of thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie correction; and neuer to ſcourge thee againe by my former offences, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="meditation">
                  <pb n="319" facs="tcp:12413:162"/>
                  <head>The 13. Meditation, at fiue a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thy ſacred eies being hid and blindfoulded, thoſe ſacrilegious wretches gaue vnto thee ſundrie blowes and buffets, ſaying. Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto vs o Chriſt, who he was that ſmote thee, Deare Ieſus, hide not from me the eyes of thy mercie: nor let me hide mine owne, by thinkinge when I ſinne, that thou dooſt not ſee me. And prophecie vnto me, o Chriſt, what, and who I am, that ſo often, with the hand of my wicked workes, haue ſo daringlie, and ſo auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſlie ſmitten thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="meditation">
                  <pb n="320" facs="tcp:12413:163"/>
                  <head>The 14. Meditation, at ſix a clock in the morning</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thou (king of all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (waſt clothed in a purple garment, crowned with a crowne of Thornes, and a hollow Reede was giuen into thy handes inſteede of a Sceptie. Deare Ieſus, grant me neuer to put vpon thee by mockerie, a kinglie gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by doing good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for any vaine glorious end: to remember by this hollow Reede, the hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and inſtabillitie of all temporall thinges: and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie to weare the crowne of thornes, and of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, in this world, ſo that I may weare the crowne of
<pb n="321" facs="tcp:12413:163"/> glorie in the world to come, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 15. Meditation, at 7. a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre. Pontius Pilate brought thee foorth, and ſhewed thee vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this pittifull plight, ſayinge. <hi>Behould the man,</hi> profferring them Barrabas, to deliuer thee: but they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantlie cried out aloud to haue thee crucified: Deare Ieſus, grant me, that being at any time afflicted with temptations, I may preſent this figure vnto thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing. <hi>Behould the man.</hi> And to beare it moſt patientlie, though wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked or inferior parſons be
<pb n="322" facs="tcp:12413:164"/> preferred before me, ſith a thiefe and murdrer was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 16. Meditation, at 8. a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O good Ieſus. In this houre, Pilat ouercome with the importunat clamors of the Iewes, pronounced the ſentence of death againſt thee: and Iudas caſting downe the mony, deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, hung him ſelfe vpon a tree. Deare Ieſus, pardon me, who many times in fauour of the world, and myne owne fleſh, haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the ſentence of death againſt thee; And grant me perfect Contrition for all my ſinnes, ſo that I neuer, finallie deſpaire of
<pb n="323" facs="tcp:12413:164"/> thy grace and mercie. Amen</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 17. Meditation, at 9 a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre the Iewes pullinge off the clothes of mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which Herod and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates ſoldiers had put vpon thee, and reueſtinge thee with thine owne apparell, that thou mighſt the better be knowen, thou carriedſt thy heauie C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſſe towards the mount of Caluarie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen till thou felſt downe in the way for exceſſiue wearines: Deare Ieſus, grant me hereby to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that at the laſt, death will deſpoile me, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the world hath lent
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:12413:165"/> me. And make me neuer to be wearie, of bearing thy Croſſe, that being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of thy paine, I may be partaker of thy glorie, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 18. Meditation, at 10. a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thou waſt crucified on the Croſſe betwixt two theeues, thy B bodie being ſo violentlie extended ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that one might number all thy bones: meane while thou praiedſt for thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies, and promiſedſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe vnto the penitent thiefe. Deare Ieſus, cauſe me to crucifie all my diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered appetites, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all my members, with
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:12413:165"/> all the powers both of ſoule and bodie, in the ſeruice of thee; And at the houre of my death, vouch-ſafe to doe me the ſelfe ſame grace, that thon didſt vnto the penitent thiefe, and to thoſe that crucified thee, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 19. Meditation, at 11. a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thine enimies moſt ſpitefullie vpbraidinge thee, that if thou wert the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of God, thou ſhouldſt come downe from the Croſſe and ſaue thy ſelfe; meane while, thou ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfullie criedſt out to thy Father, ſaying. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken</hi>
                     <pb n="326" facs="tcp:12413:166"/> 
                     <hi>me?</hi> Deare Ieſus, grant vnto me. that by no ſuggeſtion of the world, the fleſh, or the deuill, I euer come downe from the Croſſe of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. Nor euer to deſpaire in myne aduerſities, though it ſeeme vnto me to be quite forſaken, ſith the like deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation did happen to thee hauing on the Croſſe, in ſuch extremitie, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 20 Meditation, at 12. a clock at noone.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre, crauing a litle drincke to quench thy thirſt, they gaue thee moſt bitter gaule and vinegre to encreaſe thy torment, which hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, cryinge with a loud voice; <hi>All is finished</hi> thou rendredſt vp thy ſpirit into
<pb n="327" facs="tcp:12413:166"/> the handes of thy Father. Deare Ieſus, make me neuer to abuſe the good crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ures of mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e or drinke, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and vinegre was giuen to thee. Conſtantlie to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u, euen to the end, that I may trulie ſay with thee, <hi>All is finished</hi> which thou haſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me: and ſo may recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſoule into thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> holie handes, extended;, pierced, and with thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood, all beſprinkled for me, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 21. Meditation, at one a clocke in the after-noone.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre, the ſunne was dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the earth trembled, the rocks rent a ſundre; the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:12413:167"/> opened, and many that ſlept aroſe, went foorth, and appeared to diuers in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Deare Ieſus, wound my hart with ſuch compaſſion, that like to the ſunne it may quite looſe the light of all wordlie ioye. Like to the earth, to tremble with feare. Like to the rocks, to rent with ſorrow. Like to the graues to open by confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Like to the dead, to ariſe and goe foorth of the ſepulchre of ſinne. And like vnto thoſe Saints, enter into the citie of paradiſe &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting pleaſure, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 22. Meditation, at 2. a clock in the morning.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, in this houre, thy moſt holy ſoule, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended
<pb n="329" facs="tcp:12413:167"/> into the priſon of Limbo, to deliuer from thence thy faithfull frindes, meane while, the ſacred ſide of thy dead bodie, was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the ſtroake of a ſoldiers ſpeare. Deare Ieſus, make me willingly for the loue of thee, to viſit priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the ſoules in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or any poore that are in neceſſitie. Wound my hart perfectlie with the loue of thee, and let this moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred wound, ſtand allwayes open vnto me in my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 23. Meditation, at 3. a clock in the afternone.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre, Ioſeph entring bould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to Pilat, and begging
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:12413:168"/> thy bodie, with the helpe of Nicodemus, vnnailed, and tooke downe the ſame from the tree of the Croſſe: and coming towards the earth, was receiued of thy bleſſed mother betwixt hir armes. Deare Ieſus, grant me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire with loue, and to beg with faith, thy bleſſed body in the holie Euchariſt; And to reciue thee often within the armes of my ſoule, with ſuch burning teares of loue and deuotion, as did thy ſad and afflicted mother, Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="meditation">
                  <head>The 24. Meditation, at 4. a clock in the afternone.</head>
                  <p>O Good Ieſus, In this houre thy welbeloued frinds annointed thy dead bodie
<pb n="331" facs="tcp:12413:168"/> with moſt pretious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: wrapped the ſame in a cleane ſindon, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie, encloſed the ſame within a new ſepulchre, wherin neuer any was laid, or buried before. Deare Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, vouchſafe to annoint my ſoule, when it ſhall be dead by ſinne, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious liquor of thy preue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient grace. And grant (I beſeeche thee) that my hart may be vnto thee a new ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre (trulie renewed in newnes of life) wherin thou onlie and thy celeſtiall loue, may be lodged and incloſed, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:169"/>
                  <head>Saluations to all the partes of Chriſt and recommandation of himſelfe vnto him.</head>
                  <p>AL I hail ô head of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, dreadfull to all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, crowned for vs with thornes, and ſmitten with a reed. All hail ô moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full face of our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, ſpit at and buffeted for vs. All hail ô moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigne eyes of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed for vs with teares. All hail ô honny-flowinge mouth, and throat moſt ſweet of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, made for vs to drink gall and vineger. All hail ô moſt noble eares of our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:12413:169"/> vexed with contumelies and vpbraidings for vs. All hail ô humble necke of Ieſu Chriſt buffeted for vs, and moſt holy back whipped for vs. All hail ô moſt venerable handes and armes of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, ſtretched vpon the Croſſe for vs. All hail ô moſt meek breſt of our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, much troubled for vs in thy paſſion. All hail ô moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſide of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt pearced through with the ſpeare of a ſoldier for vs. All hail ô ſacred knees of mercie of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſt bowed for vs in thy prayers. All hail (ô feete to be adored) of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, faſtened with nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:12413:170"/> for vs. All hail ô holie body of Ieſu Chriſt, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the Croſſe, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;, dead and buried for vs. All hail ô moſt pretious bloud of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſt, powred out for vs. All hail ô moſt holy ſoule of our Lord Ieſu Chriſt, recommended vpon the Croſſe for vs into the handes of thy Father. In the ſame recommandation, I recommend to thee this day, and daily, my ſoule, my life, my hart, and body, all my ſenſes and acts, all my friendes and benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, my ſonnes and kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks, the ſoule of my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, brethren, ſiſters, and of all my friendes and eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: that thow voutſafe
<pb facs="tcp:12413:170"/> to protect, deliuer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs from all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of our enimies vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and inuiſible, now and for euer more. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:171"/>
                  <head>APPROBATIO.</head>
                  <p>LIbellum hunc piaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Meditationum pro 24. diei horis, legi attente: &amp; nihil inuenio quod ſit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra fidem aut bonos mores; ſed dignum iudico qui pro ſolatio deuotorum imprima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. 4. Ianuarij. 1618.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>F. Leander de S. Martin Benedictoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Anglorum Vicarius generalis, S. Theol. Doct. &amp; Regius Profeſsor linguae Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctae in Academia Duacena.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12413:171"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
